I called this meeting.
Oops.
Mm-mm.
I'm going to figure that one out.
That's pretty cool.
All set.
Oops. Into eternity.
All right.
This will go project, right?
All right. That sounds a lot better to me.
I call this meeting to order, this meeting of the South Portland City
Council on April 21st,
2026.
If you'd like to stand with me and show your respect for the
multicultural republic that is the United States of
America. I pledge allegiance to the
flag of the United States of America and
to the republic for which it stands, one
nation under God, indivisible, with
liberty and justice for all.
Thank you.
Madam Clerk, may we have a roll call, please?
Councilor Scott?
Councilor Walker?
Yep.
Sorry, I'm on.
There we go.
Carter Scott's on.
Hi, Carter Scott. We hear you.
Thank you.
Councilor Coleman?
Here.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Here.
Councilor Pride?
And Mayor Dixon?
Here.
If there are no objections, we're going to pass our minutes by
unanimous consent.
Seeing none, the minutes are passed.
We have petitions and communications, and I think our city clerk
has an announcement to make.
Thank you. This is just a formal communication that we did
receive the resignation of school board member Adrian Dowling
on the 6th of April.
This is for District 5 seat, expiring in December of
2027. Per our charter, this is a vacancy that can be
filled by the council. This petition is just to formally address the
process that they may choose to select someone to be appointed
before the November election.
But as you will see later on the agenda this evening,
I have added an agenda item to formally accept the resignation and to put this
position on the ballot for November, so that we will have the petition papers
available in July to fill the seat for the remainder of its term.
Thank you very much.
You'll see the next item is our appointment calendar.
With no objection, we're going to postpone that to our next
meeting.
I don't see objections. That is postponed.
And now we move to the consent calendar.
But before we get to our consent calendar, we read the rules
for public comment, which will follow the consent
calendar.
Members of the public are invited to comment on any topic on or off the agenda
during citizen discussion part one or part two for up to three minutes.
If you are here to speak on an item appearing on tonight's agenda, you are
encouraged to wait until this item comes up on the agenda where you will have three
minutes to speak.
If you are unable to wait, you may speak on the matter during citizen discussion
part one. However, you will not be permitted to speak on that topic
again. Members of the public who speak on the topic when it comes up on the agenda
may not speak up on the topic during citizen discussion part
two. We ask all speakers to clearly state your name and address for the record.
Thank you.
And I'd like to acknowledge that we're in a different little home today, our city
council. We're usually nested back at City Hall.
Today, we're here in order to allow for more room
for folks, since we anticipate public comment on
some of our issues. And
I also wanted to mention that for public comment, you will
see a timer that tells you
how many seconds you have
left.
The other thing I wanted to mention is that it's a hybrid meeting
today, so we should be seeing the faces of folks
who are speaking. There is the face of Councilor
Scott. And the only thing
is, this is a plus and a minus. The plus is that our
wonderful SPTV people have gone to great lengths
to ensure that we have hybrid-worthy technology
tonight. But in the event of an issue, the meeting
is going on, in the event of a technology issue.
So, I just want that to be known.
Okay.
Let's go back to our consent calendar and have you read it. Thank you.
Absolutely.
Proclamation recognizing the South Portland Little League 75th Anniversary.
Proclamation recognizing the month of May as ALS Awareness
Month in South Portland.
Order 180-25-26, accepting the resignation of
Adrian Dowling from School Board District 5, effective April 6th,
2026, and directing the city clerk to place the school board seat on the
November 3rd, 2026 ballot for an unexpired term expiring on December of
2027.
Order 181-25-26, appointing Peter Connell representing Oceans Property
under Sebago Gulf LLC to the Long Creek Watershed Management
District Board of Directors as a representative of the private participating
landowner seat.
Order 182-25-26, setting the time and opening of our
polling locations on June 9th, 2026, for the state primary and school budget
validation referendum election.
Order number 183-25-26, appointing election clerks for a two-year term
expiring May 1st.
Order 184-25-26, appointing Alexandria Grindle as warden
pro tem for District 3 for an unexpired term until November of
2028.
Order 185-25-26, appointing Don Russell for pro tem ward clerk for
District 2 for the June 9th and the November 3rd
elections. And order 1862526.
Award of bid number 2426 for DCM Construction Services for minor
renovations work related to the finance office to provide better
customer service in the amount of $38,500 for contingency
funds. All items read on the consent calendar require a majority vote.
Thank you very much. Councilors, is there anything you would like to
remove from the consent calendar?
Okay. This is a new setup, and I'm used to seeing
them a little closer to me.
All right. Well, I don't see anything that needs to be
removed. We have an opportunity to make public comment
on items that are on the consent calendar.
Again, public comment on the consent calendar.
After that, we'll have public comment that is our open public
comment, that is any subject that you would like to address.
And then public comment is offered for each item on the
agenda. So as long as that's clear to everybody, you'll know where
you do and don't want to fit. Thank you.
Any consent calendar items?
I don't see any, so public comment on the consent
calendar is closed. Councilors,
can we
move for-
Move for passage.
Second.
Seconded by Councilor Pride.
Councilor,
did you want to say... No.
No.
Okay. So we're going to, without objection, pass by
unanimous consent. Yay. But you get to see us raise our hands anyway because we're
a little... Yes?
Don't you have to do when you have somebody not present-
Roll call... when you have-
Oh, that's right. We're doing roll call votes. I'm sorry.
We're doing roll call votes because we're hybrid.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Councilor Scott?
Approved.
Councilor Walker?
Yes.
Councilor Coleman?
Councilor Pride?
Yes.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Yes, ma'am.
And Mayor Tipton.
Yes. Thank you.
All right. I think we have a little special something to do now.
One of the items you'll notice on our consent calendar
is a proclamation relating to Little League, and
I don't know if we would call you the sponsor of that proclamation, but that's
probably the right name, would be Councilor Matthews.
And I think what we want to do is invite some of the Little Leaguers and their
families, and anyone who is affiliated with Little League to come
on up, have a picture, and actually receive the proclamation.
Hi.
And as everyone is coming through, I'll just read the proclamation for the public.
Whereas South Portland Little League was founded in 1951 with the first games
played that year, providing seven decades of youth and family in South
Portland with the opportunity to participate in organized baseball and softball.
Whereas the program grew in the years that followed to include multiple
local leagues, including South Portland American Little
League, South Portland National Little League, Sunset Park Little League-
Yes
... South Portland Central Little League, reflecting the community's strong and
sustainable commitment to the Little League.
Whereas for 75 years, tens of thousands of children in our community have
developed skills, confidence, teamwork, sportsmanship through participation
in the Little League programs, including T-ball, baseball, softball, and the
Challengers Division for players of all abilities.
Whereas softball programs were established and evolved over time, ultimately
rejoining Little League to further unify and strengthen youth softball and
baseball in South Portland.
Whereas the success and longevity of the South Portland Little League has been made
possible by the dedication
of countless volunteers, including coaches, umpires, board members, local
business sponsors, families who have generously contributed their time and
resources.
You're good.
Whereas South Portland Little League has played an important role in strengthening
community pride and providing a safe and inclusive, enriching environment for our
youth and recreation.
Whereas the 75th year of South Portland Little League represents a significant
milestone worthy of recognition and celebration across the city.
Now be it therefore proclaimed by the City Council of South Portland,
recognizing the year of 2026 as South Portland's Little League 75th
anniversary year, and we encourage all residents to join and celebrate this
milestone in recognizing the lasting impact in South Portland Little League in our
community.
I'll see you guys on opening day, okay?
And we'll present this to the rest of the league. Good job tonight, guys.
Yay.
All right.
I
got
it.
It's my job.
I'm going to adjourn the... Oh. Good job.
All right. I think we are back in action for
some public comment.
Do we have anyone who would like to make public comment on an item
on or off the agenda? Although we do recommend if it's on the
agenda, you hold it until then.
Don't be shy.
All right. Looks like we do not. Oh.
Anything?
On anything on or off the agenda. If you want to wait for the agenda item, that's
fine, too.
What is it with you guys?
Yeah. Okay.
Psst. You can't do both.
Folks, you could help me save a life.
I'm going to ask you to grab your pen
I'm getting there.
I'm going to ask you to grab a pen and your paper, and I'm going to fly through
this.
Are you doing the three minutes or is Jessica?
Yes.
All right. We ask that you give us your name, and it would be nice
if you want to say where you live. You can give your street address.
Okay. My name is Dave Hebert. I live on Edward Street.
Thank you.
Okay.
Let me know when it's time.
Sure.
Jordan's got you going.
Okay.
This is a proactive approach instead of a reactive
approach.
This has to do with
K Lupa 22 shipyard and terminal area policy B.
At the last comprehensive plan meeting, the word potential
was added,
saying potential significant VOC emissions, which
acknowledges the current empty tanks could become active as long
as they're licensed to. This is great.
I thank both the CBC in planning for adding that.
From a functional perspective, this does very little unless we
add some proactive language with it.
For example, in correspondence with the DEP, I asked whether the DEP
or CDC forecasts future emissions from bulk
petroleum storage terminals using historical data.
Her reply, "No, the DEP does not forecast emissions.
Instead, permits are based on a facility's maximum
potential to emit."
The term potential to emit is a formal regulatory
concept used by the main DEP. It is not a
forecast or an estimate of future conditions, but a legally defined
maximum level of emissions allowed under a facility's permit.
This is really important to understand if you truly want to help people
or keep people safe. In the last few years, Sunoco was operating at
30% of their legal potential to emit, again, based on
throughput and tank activity. These are calculated
emissions from the terminal sent to the DEP every year.
However, that level isn't fixed. From 2015 to
2018, throughput was significantly higher, at 60%,
twice the amount.
Concurrently, the DEP is collecting emissions samples and sending them to the
CDC. This is where the data comes from, which is used to
create the charts the CDC presents at meetings.
It is also the evidence-based data where it is rooted in that,
which is proposed policy that it talks about in the plan.
If the planning decisions are informed by emissions that are measured with sampling
during low throughput, then the facility later operates
closer to its permitted maximum potential to emit.
You can see how the term evidence-based becomes really spongy,
which can be dangerous for any future residents of that property,
totally misrepresenting reality.
30 seconds.
What I suggest, after the line that ends with "Demonstrate acceptable
conditions for long-term occupancy," add the following,
"The evaluation must incorporate
maximum potential to emit values for ensuring
safety for the long term."
Those words, maximum potential emissions, are exactly as the DEP
worded it
and how they look in the future.
Time.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
You know what?
We're not going to do clapping or booing or finger
snapping or hissing because one,
it's
going to take us a long time to get through, and two, it does
kind of maybe discourage people who, if they hear clapping for one
kind of opinion, might not be encouraged to offer a different
opinion. So I'll just put that out there.
One thing that I also
thought I'd told you every rule that was ever written, but to
keep in mind is that on a particular subject, you can
comment once. So just making sure people know that,
too.
All right. If there is anyone else who wants to make a public comment
on or off the agenda. I don't see anyone.
That comment period-
No, she's up.
Up, up, up. Almost. Come on, don't be shy, all y'all.
Come on down.
Make a line-
Make sure you-
... if there's going to be multiple.
Okay. Or ask if anybody... Help me keep track of if
anybody's there.
Yeah.
Hi, Pam Thomas, Alder Street, and
21-year resident and 14-year manufacturing
company in South Portland co-owner.
Look across the harbor. Portland has a sliver of land with
high-rises hovering over it, shading the waterfront trail and
shoreline every afternoon. Cruise ships block the
wind for small boats and kids as teens and adults and kids try to
reach the harbor without an engine.
On our side of the harbor, once the tanks are gone
and the contaminated land is cleared, cleaned, excuse me,
imagine open space. Imagine enhanced public
access to the waterfront. Imagine families having elbow
room to blanket on the grass and picnic.
This prime, unobstructed waterfront
location should be shared with all residents
and visitors, not just the wealthy few.
A sliver of land is not going to cut it.
Fort Williams in Cape Elizabeth is 90 acres.
Bug Light Park is less than nine acres.
I encourage you to bring back K Lupa 27 as the Eastern
Marine Protection Area. I request that you downgrade
the growth designation to limited or conservation.
Let's permit a resilient park in this flood zone rather
than high-rise condos and businesses that we will eventually have to
bail out.Let's give the SOS group time
to organize and seek funding from national organizations for a
resilient park. Please slow down and think
big.
As taxpayers, we already see and understand the
pressure on our aging water treatment plant, our schools, our public
transportation, our fire rescue services, our boat
launch, our beach, our roads, and in particular, Broadway.
When Ferry Village floods with sea level rise, we will be
overwhelmed and out of money, and as a result, you will increase
taxes on all residents because of the impact of building in a
flood zone at the tip of a peninsula
with a drawbridge adjacent to toxic fumes.
I ask you this, please Google an article.
It's by Fast Company. It's The Four Best Waterfront
Parks of 2025 That Transform Shorelines into-
30 seconds
... City Centerpieces. Again, Fast Company article,
Best Shorelines of Waterfront Parks 2025, and thank you so much.
I think it will inspire you.
Thank you very much, Ms. Thomas.
Hello. You've heard from me before, but I don't know where I am on the
agenda. So my name is Leslie Gatcombe Hines,
and I live at 47 Elmwood Avenue. I previously expressed my
thoughts on the comprehensive plan to the council and reiterate them.
I think that precious shoreline property should be reserved for marine and
recreational use that unlike hotels
or other businesses that could be located elsewhere.
Particularly in regard to lands likely to be submerged from rising sea levels, I
disagree with placing any residential or non-marine commercial buildings there.
The tax base also needs to be considered, as any construction requires
infrastructure, much of which is aging.
For example, my street continues to be hit with a lot of runoff from higher ground
water and threatened with flooding from future sea level rise,
and the sewer drainage is inadequate for the task, for which I have
brought to all the city authorities that I can.
And the issue of oil tanks and past business use also needs to be addressed.
About, I think it was about seven years ago when we gathered
samples from the air.
I brought home one of those vacuum tanks, placed it on my deck, and it just goes
and took a sample of air. When I released the seal, that
sample was sucked in. The air was found to be contaminated with volatile
organic chemicals.
I have lived in South Portland most of my adult life, 21 years in my
current home,
and I'm being treated right now for cancer.
I had genetic testing that can
determine that my type of cancer is not genetic, therefore it must be
environmental.
So I am concerned with the EPA maps which show my neighborhood as being at
moderate cancer risk.
Many cancers are environmentally caused, and we need to do what we can to mitigate
that risk.
And finally, I also had advocated that all South Portland residents should have
easy walking access to green space, and this is important for both the physical and
mental health of our inhabitants and wildlife.
South Portland has a good environmental record, and I would like to see that
continue.
I'm here for the planet. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Hello, my name is Edward Reiner. I live on 25 Ballard Street.
I too, am in cancer treatment right now
for bladder cancer. My
house is at the end of Elm Street. We're about 700 feet from the
Global and Sprague tanks.
I've recently been interviewed by The Boston Globe about the hazards in that
neighborhood. One of my conclusions was that there should be
epidemiological studies so we actually know how many people are
being sickened.
I'm reminded of Tom Blake's, the
previous mayor, Tom Blake's efforts in the tar sands and
how
valiantly he fought to protect the public
health, and it resulted in a positive decision for the Clear
Skies ordinance. I was inspired by that, knowing that he
himself felt he grew up
and was sickened by... lifelong resident on the waterfront here.
So my conclusions about
the property near Bug Light is that before anything is built,
the health hazards, the air quality has to be considered
before going forward, as well as the consideration we
just heard about the floodplain being a limiting factor.
And I'm highly in favor of
waterfront access and open space.
That's what we need in an urban area.
And one of my reflections on living in South Portland, it's a very
livable city other than our problems with air quality.
So keeping green space and recreational opportunities,
I fly kites with my granddaughters at Bug Light, and I
would like them to be able to feel that there's some nature beyond Bug Light
that's just nine acres. So
I'm asking you to consider to go slowly and
consider those
considerations of air quality and the floodplain
and open space. I think those all have to be taken into consideration.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
My name is Carolyn Foley. I live on the high ground by Willard Beach.
With the flooding, you guys are welcome to come to my house.
It's only 1,000 square feet, but you're welcome to come and stay with me.
I am a biker and a pedestrian, and I fear that all the extra people
and all the extra cars
are going to cause more safety issues.
Right now, a 10-year-old can barely get across Broadway, so the traffic is
just absolutely horrible.
I bike. I've been biking
for 40 years or so
So it's not a problem, but people who are inexperienced might not be able to bike
on Broadway anymore, might not be able to get across the street, especially with
SMCC cars and the kids who don't really care because it's not their neighborhood.
I just think that with adding so many people into
that area and so many cars, it's just going to be really an issue.
I don't know how you're going to plan on doing that.
Maybe we can start a boat ferry ride across the harbor so that people who work
in Portland don't have to travel all the way around.
Traffic is already really tough at rush hour traffic.
I'm sure that all you guys know that because you all live here.
I also want to know who is going to benefit from the monies, from the finances
from building these things. Is it only going to be the people who are
building it and are selling it at high prices even though there's going to be some
affordable housing of like $600,000? So that's it.
Thank you very much.
Hi there. My name is Milo Small.
I live at 41 Pier Street
over in Ferry Village.
I don't have a speech
prepared. These are just my thoughts.
I've lived in that neighborhood for my whole
life.
I've inherited this house from my aunt.
She passed away from cancer at 61.
And
if the City of South Portland knows that they're
building within a flood zone, my question is: Why is that
even a consideration?
And what is the goal for adding this infrastructure?
I plan on living in this house and in this neighborhood for the rest of my life,
and to know that I
run past these tanks every single morning,
and to know that they're
actively contributing to my risk of cancer
is
devastating.
I want to live here.
We all know the housing market,
of affording a place to live and move.
My family lives here.
This is where I want to be,
and
I'm asking
the people in this room
to
see that.
On another note,
I went to
a capstone research probably two years ago over
in the Portland Public Library, where many
colleges were presenting, and
a Harvard student.
They were architecture students
who were trying to build infrastructure after the sea levels rise, and they
had a map
of Portland and South Portland, and my property happens to be on this
map.
And by 2050, it
says the sea level will rise by 1.5 feet.
By 2070, it will rise by three feet.
And if this-
30 seconds
... infrastructure is built,
what is the City of South Portland going to do
after?
Is it going to be demolitioned?
The neighborhood,
there's just going to be buildings
submerged in three feet of water.
That doesn't sound, in terms of longevity,
these buildings should last for more than
30 years, 40 years.
Time.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay, coming on down.
Hey, everyone.
So good evening. My name is Jeremy Naden, and I live at Clinton Street.
November 2024 election, voters
added Section 204.2 to the charter, so Bug Light, Mill Creek, and
Hinckley Parks can't be sold or traded away without a referendum.
This protection only exists because residents brought it.
It keeps Bug Light from being sold. It doesn't keep it from being encircled.
Bug Light sits in between rising water on one side and proposed
residential rezoning up to six stories on the other.
Prior waterfront residential proposal was withdrawn after sustained opposition,
but opposition has continued in the thousands through petition signatures
validated by the city clerk.
The 2040 comprehensive plan has been in progress for years, but the ground
has shifted since. LD 2003 in 2022
and LD 1829 in 2025 changed what a city
controls once it adopts growth designations.
Tonight, I want to name three gaps in the plan as written.
Who pays? South Portland sewer rates are set to rise 22%, as
reported every year for three years,
with about $50 million needed in wastewater work.
Broadway already carries 24,000 vehicles a day through
bottlenecks
with no funded relief. Growth without funded infrastructure shifts
those costs onto the residents already here.
Environmental sea level rise, we heard about projections up
to as high as eight to 8.8 feet by 2120.
Emissions concerns persist. These impact the same
land the plan designates for growth.
And third, process. Residents have been providing input to this plan since
2022, myself included. A plan shaped by three years of
resident input should not be adopted without a fresh read against the modified
state laws that will actually govern it.Residents have shown up,
signed, spoken, and paid attention.
We deserve answers on the record before the vote, not after it.
I'd also ask the council to be alert to the broader pressure this plan sits
within. Regional business groups are on the record advocating to shift
land use authority away from local governments.
So my ask is narrow and concrete. Amend the plan to remove or
defer the eastern waterfront growth designations while key concerns
are addressed, and delay the vote long enough to reassess how the
main growth laws actually apply to what we are about to adopt.
Hard things can be accomplished. In 2014, the city won a federal lawsuit over
the Clear Skies Ordinance. In decades past, Cape Elizabeth bought Fort
Williams. Portland preserved the-
30 seconds
... Eastern Promenade. We owe the residents already here a plan that holds
up, not one that leaves them asking for the next 15 years
what it should answer now.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Is there anyone else who would like to make a comment now?
All right. You're absolutely sure? I have this little hammer.
No.
All right. We're going to close this public comment.
There will be more opportunities.
Let's move to public hearings-
Questions.
Oh, we do have questions to answer. I know.
I guess I'd look to the planning director.
I know you've been taking copious notes and are planning to provide answers.
I don't know if any might be covered in your presentation too, but feel free to
address the ones that you heard.
Well, I have a few direct questions since they're all comp plan related.
Do you want me to bundle these with the later comp plan questions?
I don't know if those folks will stick around.
Why don't we try it right this second?
Milana Vito, the planning director.
I caught three specific questions that were raised.
The first
was who benefits from the buildings?
I think the context there was the buildings that would be allowed if we adopt a
growth
designation and then adopt the zoning, and then proposals are
submitted, and they meet the standards that are proposed.
Who would benefit from the profit, I guess, from those buildings or
the finances of those buildings?
And it would be the city through the collection of taxes and possibly some
other things. We know, for instance, we collect fees through the development
application process and the construction process.
We collect sewer rates from developments at the
time of connection. The plan calls for certain things like impact fees,
which we're developing now based on council funding from two years
prior for things like sewer traffic, and we can do other things as
well. If those are in effect, we would collect all of those kinds of
fees. If we implement a tax increment financing district, we could collect
those sheltered dollars, which wouldn't happen otherwise.
And then there's the property taxes, and if there's businesses there, there's also
the personal property of those businesses that would all generate revenues for the
city.
So that's sort of the city side of the ledger, and I might be missing something.
Scott, our finance director, can weigh in on that.
But if the development is moving forward and it's a for-profit development, there's
very likely, after accounting for those things, profit that's intended
to be gained as well for the private parties that are making those investments.
The second question I got is what is the goal with adding this infrastructure?
I think again, the context is by allowing development within areas.
I think they were characterizing it as areas
where we project floodwaters to be.
And the goal, it's not a singular goal.
The plan outlines multiple goals, and what I think
will be presented later in the presentation and was
tried to be expressed within the plan is that there's multiple competing
things that the community has to balance, and the policies in the plan try to
strike a balance between those things.
So yes, there is concerns around things like VOCs and
the air emissions and the
health conditions of the air, the floodwaters and where they're going, the traffic
on Broadway, the urban design, the access to open space, the bike ped facilities,
but there's also concerns around housing, fiscal revenues,
creating community, creating access, creating open space without always
doing it at the resident taxpayer's expense.
And in trying to strike that balance, we're trying to hit on all of those goals.
So there's economic development goals, there's housing goals, there's environmental
goals, there's open space goals, there's remediation of brownfields goals.
And what the committee has tried to strike is a balance of
allowing some forms of development to try and achieve all of those goals
but establish enough protections to avoid the risks.
And then I'm not sure if this was framed as a question, but I did circle it.
It was in the final comment there in reference to specifically recent
legislation that was passed at the state level that forces communities
to do certain things
in some cases based on how we designate areas,
whether they're growth or non-growth areas.
And I just wanted to at least make the statement, and I'm happy to go into it
deeper, is that this comprehensive plan fully responds to all of the
current legislation and the legislation that we're aware of that hasn't been passed
so that we're not at odds with any
of that. And the growth designations that we have are not at odds with what the
state has already expressed an interest in putting forward or what the state has
already passed.
I will also highlight that those changes from 2003, LD 2003 and
LD 1829,
the general
description of those and their impacts in the development world is
significantly larger than what the actual legislation does.
For instance, LD 1829 is only active up to the first four units.
It doesn't go beyond that. It doesn't enable indiscriminate development at 40 units
per acre or something like that.
So we've been tracking all of those bills and absorbed them into the plan, and the
CPC, the Comprehensive Plan Committee, has reviewed what that
legislation imposes and how to
respond.Well, I'll leave it there if-
There was a question about,
I think this was related to if it's built, so if there's a new development,
and I guess this could apply to existing development too, that becomes
underwater. What does the city do then?
I don't know if that's anything you can respond to in relation to the comp
plan.
Sure.
And some of the context there, I think, was a citation from,
I guess, some student mapping that was made available,
referenced to 1.5 feet and 3 feet of sea level rise was
that risk category. This plan requires us to prepare for at a
minimum of 3.9 feet, so 1 foot above what
was projected there, and up to 8.8 feet if we go
to slightly larger scale developments or more critical infrastructure, things like
city halls and whatnot.
So we're preparing for significantly more.
In fact, this plan would make South Portland the only community in the
nation to actually try to prepare for an 8.8-foot scenario.
No one else has done it or even come close to doing that.
So the benchmark for what qualifies as a building that's
capable of being there for the long term
is
a singular thing that only South Portland has defined as 8.8 feet.
If it can't meet that threshold, it won't be a development that can
proceed. So from the get-go, if a new building is proposed,
it will certainly be able to weather those conditions or have to
demonstrate that it can weather those conditions.
There's also policy in the plan that says the council has zero
obligation, and in fact, no expectation, which is breaking from the
norm from decades ago, to accept any infrastructure that's
proposed in areas that you deem are potential at-risk areas.
So where, for instance, the Outer Highland Subdivisions, when
they got built, a lot of those roads ended up turning into public roads.
That's very common and very normal.
Councils have always had the discretion to say, "No, thanks.
We don't want that public park donated to us.
Let it be private with public access.
We don't want that road." "We don't want to own that sewer system." The Sable Oaks
area, for instance, has a private sewer system. We never accepted it.
City councils have always had that discretion, but they've never, or
typically erred on the side of absorbing it.
This plan says explicitly the council needs to do the due diligence of figuring
out if any infrastructure should be absorbed as a public infrastructure.
And if not, those remain the burden of the development to maintain and
make sure that it's functional for
that area. So we've tried to put in the checks and balances to make sure that the
city is not paying for infrastructure it doesn't want to pay for, and that in the
long term, it's not holding the bag for infrastructure
that was serving a private development.
Okay.
That's all I have. Yep.
All right. Thank you, Milan.
And thank you to folks who asked questions.
I feel like we've had a little bit of an appetizer for what might come
later. We're moving to public hearings and action now.
Madam City Clerk, could you read Ordinance
2025-26?
Ordinance number 2025-26, amending Chapter 4, Bicycles, of the Code of
Ordinances to update the definition of a bicycle and add definition for the
electric bicycle to better align with the state definition.
Second reading. First reading was approved on April 7th, 2026.
Passage will require a majority vote, and again, this will be a roll call vote.
Thank you. Help me to remember that.
Counselors, do you have questions on this item?
I don't see any council questions.
We can open this item up for public comment.
Anyone have public comment on this item, please come to the microphone.
Anyone? All right.
We're going to close public comment on this item.
And
counselors, any discussion? I don't think so.
It is a second read. So anyone? Anyone?
We do have some discussion.
Oh, no discussion.
No, you're-
Just move for passage of the second read
... you're moving for passage. Okay. A second. Thank you.
That was Counselor Walker moving, Counselor West seconding.
Can we have our roll call vote?
I'm going to ask for comments.
Oh, do you have comments?
I do. Just to say to some members of the community who have
communicated with me on this, that what we're doing is bringing our
definition of bicycle into conformance with state law.
State law defines bicycle to include Class 1 and Class 2
electric bikes. Therefore, if we allow bicycles on the green belt,
it means we allow Class 1 and Class 2 electric bikes.
It's not us doing anything different.
It's just following state law.
Thank you, Counselor West.
All right. And you, no?
Nothing to add.
Counselor Walker? Okay. So now we're having our roll call vote.
Counselor Matthews?
Yes, ma'am.
Counselor West?
Yes.
Counselor Pride?
Counselor Scott?
Yes.
Counselor Walker?
Counselor Coleman?
Yes.
And Mayor Tipton.
Yes, thank you.
All right. That ordinance passes unanimously. Thank you.
Let's move to the next one, number 21.
Ordinance number 2125-26, amending Chapter 15, Motor
Vehicles and Traffic, of our Code of Ordinances to update the definition of
bicycle. Again, this is a second read.
The first reading passed on April 7th, 2026.
This will require a majority vote, and again, will be a roll call vote.
Thank you very much. Counselors, have questions developed since our first reading?
Mm-mm.
I don't see questions. Do we have public comment on this item?
Ordinance 21.
Don't-
Does that include speed regulations, since electric bikes is
normally traveling faster?
All right.
Okay. To refresh my
memory, what's your name again?
Edward Reiner.
Okay.
Reiner.
We prefer you come to the microphone if that works for you.
Let me know if it doesn't.
Yes.
If you want a full comment.
Do we have an answer to the question?
There is no, in this ordinance, there is no cap on
speeds. Class one and two do have governors on them, so they can only reach certain
speeds. Class three can reach higher, but those are not allowed.
We did do a speed
study that was talked about during the first
discussion of this, and
there, generally speaking, wasn't that vast of a difference between what they
measured as what they could perceive the e-bikes were, because sometimes it's hard
to tell. But our parks staff had a hard time discerning.
But the ones they could discern, it was maybe a couple miles per
hour difference.
Right. So,
my name is Edward Reiner, 25 Ballinger.
So, I'm on the Greenbelt Trail with my bicycle a lot,
and what we've noticed, and this is true of any traffic pattern,
if
one vehicle, one bicycle is traveling significantly
faster, it's dangerous for bicyclists and
pedestrians because they're not used to
that approach or someone coming from behind that fast.
So, I'm trying to be proactive and think that also that the
class three very speedy
electric bikes may be ending up on the trail, whether they're
allowed or not. So, I'm thinking there should be some type of...
So it's on the books that
there is such a concept as speeding,
which would cover the discrepancy
between fast bicycles, people who are
bicycle athletes, and people who are going faster than that
on electric bikes. So there is a difference, I think,
between the strongest cyclists and people
on fast
electric bikes. So, my comments were just to see
if we could do something proactively rather than having to respond to
violations
or safety concerns.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. Did you want to quickly address,
would that be a workshop item or that was actually a question.
Can we proactively address this?
You could add in, if you wanted to add in speed limits.
It all goes back to the same thing that we've talked about before, the enforcement.
Right now, as you know, there's e-bikes on the Greenbelt even though they're
technically not allowed, and we don't really have much by the
way of proactive enforcement. So, we do generally have to respond
to complaints if we get them, so it would be the same thing
with speed enforcement. We don't have a dedicated person that's going to be able to
sit there with a speed gun. But understanding that,
even so, you could still put in speed restrictions.
You'd probably need to table these items and go
back and maybe revisit the prior vote because those definitions
would likely have to be updated, or this would be considered a substantive change
if you did amend it tonight, which would require another second reading.
I have one final thought there.
Oh, but you already did make a comment on this one item.
People who are proceeding-
Yeah.
On the trail-
I think-
Sorry.
Thank you. You are obviously an ideas person, but I'm going to
have to follow our rules. Thank you.
I know
what you're saying.
All right.
Yeah. Councilors, do we have someone who's moving for
passage or do we... We have Councilor West moving for passage.
We have Councilor Walker seconding, I believe.
Councilor West?
No comment.
Councilor Walker?
Second verse, same as the first.
I'll take that as no more comments. Thank you.
Is there any councilor who wants to say anything about this or anything
about
the ideas at this point?
Okay. Well, then, it looks like we're going for the vote at
this point in time.
Councilor Scott?
Yes.
Councilor Walker?
Councilor Coleman?
Yes.
Councilor Pride? Yes. Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Yes.
And Mayor Tipton.
All right.
Ordinance number 22, please, Madam City Clerk.
Ordinance number 22-25-26, amending Chapter 18, Parks and
Recreation, of the Code of Ordinances to remove the prohibition of Class 1 and
Class 2 electric bikes from operating on city property, and other miscellaneous
updates. This is a second read. First reading passed on April 7th,
2026. Passage will require a majority vote, and again, this will be a roll call
vote.
Councilors, do you have questions?
I don't see any questions.
My question is, is there anything more that we need to say about this as
relates to the state definitions, et cetera?
I would just say this. I use the
Greenbelt as well, and I do notice when people are on
e-bikes, and not that I'm a very fast biker, but I
do notice when they're going faster.
So I'd just say, if people do notice any sort of differences or if you have any
concerns with...
Sometimes there's even
ATVs that I see sometimes showing up on the Greenbelt that shouldn't be there.
If you have those concerns, please reach out to my office or our parks office that
manages the Greenbelt because we can always try to, if we
do notice some things going on that are causing problems for pedestrians or
bicyclists, we can always try to
be there if there's a common time when things are happening or whatever.
So please do reach out.
Thank you very much. I think that's quite helpful. All right.
Is there public comment on this one?
Any public comment on ordinance number 22?
You have until-
Priscilla Bird. I live on High Street,
and I live fairly close to parts of the Greenbelt,
and I like to walk on it. But I have very
limited hearing. In fact, when regular bikes
come up behind me, I don't hear the noise of the
bike, the wheels turning, until they're right beside me.
And I've turned into a little angry old lady who yells,
"Please call out when you're coming by." A few do,
but very, very few. And so I've really stopped
using the Greenbelt, and I think that electronic bikes for
me are even more dangerous, because they don't make any noise.
And some of them do go very fast, and the majority do not
call out when they come by.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. That's actually pretty important to hear.
More comment.
Come on down.
My name is David Field at 64 Summit Street.
I'm also an avid biker, and I've biked in many
cities across the country. One of the things that might be
helpful is some signage to indicate, and there may
already be some, but to indicate when passing, to ring,
to let people know or whatever. Because I think that's real helpful,
because you're walking along and all of a sudden you get startled.
So that would be my suggestion, to add some signage. Thank you.
Thank you very much. I feel like some of our comment is serving as public service
announcements. Thank you.
All right. Any more?
I don't see any more. We're going to close public comment on that item.
Councilors?
Mayor Tipton?
Yes.
Can I speak to that real quick, as a member of the Bicycle Pedestrian Committee,
to his comment about signs?
Sure. Go for it.
I just wanted to let you know they did put signs up.
The Bicycle Pedestrian Committee worked with the Public Works department to put
signs up on the Greenbelt asking people to signal when they're going
by, ask people not to ride side by side, and to
be mindful of walkers, dog walkers, children, all sorts
of other things. So they are working on that.
They're also going to have an event in August
that's kind of a public reminder to people just how to
share the Greenbelt. So
just wanted to give that information.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I think that's helpful also.
All right. Now, keeping track of where we are.
Do we have a motion for this ordinance?
Councilor West, seconded by Councilor Pride.
Any discussion from either of you? Any comments?
I just mentioned to the public that we are studying widening and
improving the Greenbelt, dependent of course, on financing, as many of our things,
and I think it would be a tremendous benefit for our community if we could improve
our Greenbelt and make it wider so that bicyclists and pedestrians can use it.
Thank you.
Agreed.
All right. Any other councilors with comments? All right.
May we have the roll call vote, please?
Councilor Scott?
Approved.
Councilor Walker?
Yes.
Councilor Coleman?
Councilor Pride?
Yes.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
No.
Mayor Tipton?
Yes.
Thank you.
All right. We'll move to ordinance number 23. Thank you.
Ordinance number 23, 25, 26, amending chapter two, administration and
legislation for miscellaneous amendments for Public Arts Committee, second reading.
First reading passed on April 7th, 2026.
This will require a majority vote, and again, will be a roll call vote.
Okay, councilors.
Again, a second reading. Any questions that have come up for you?
No.
Public comment is open on this item.
Do we have public... Oh, I see stretching. Tricked me into thinking it was a hand.
I don't see public comment on this item.
It's closed. Councilors, can we have a motion?
Move for passage.
Councilor Walker moves for passage. Councilor Coleman seconds.
Councilor Walker?
No comment.
Councilor Coleman?
Any other councilors wishing to make comment on this item?
Let's have our roll call vote, please.
Councilor Scott?
Yes.
Councilor Walker?
Councilor Coleman?
Yes.
Councilor Pride?
Councilor West?
Yes.
Councilor Matthews?
Mayor Tipton?
Yes. Thank you very much. That ordinance passes
unanimously. Ordinance number 24, please.
Ordinance number 24, 25, 26, amending chapter two, administration and
legislation, to repeal language for the Transit Advisory Committee. Second reading.
First reading passed on April 7th, 2026.
Passage will require a majority vote, and again, will be a roll call vote.
Thank you very much. I don't have a question, but I wonder if
we should repeat that by removing the
language, the committee is no longer going to be
appearing on our agendas, yes?
Is that true?
Correct.
Yeah. Say more.
So once the vote this evening passes, the ordinance
will remove the Transit Advisory Committee, and then at our
subsequent meetings, the Transit Advisory vacancies under appointment calendar
would be removed.
Thank you. And just to save, because we have so many people with us,
and transportation is obviously quite important to the council, we've
had discussions about the fact that now that Metro has
merged with South Portland and is successfully running
a bus system for us, that
South Portland is represented on the metro committees,
and that we won't need this Transit Advisory Committee
as it had existed. And we've also all said that we're grateful to those
who've served on it. So just want you all to know that, since I can see you
in front of me all wondering.
Thank you.
All right.
Councilors, other than my speech, do we have
questions?All right. This item
is open for public comment.
Do we have any public comment on this item? I don't see any.
Public comment is closed.
Move for passage.
Thank you, Councilor Matthews. Seconded by Councilor Pride.
Councilor Matthews?
I'm all good.
Thank you. Councilor Pride?
Just to add to all the things the mayor said, the Transit Advisory Committee was
also okay with this elimination of their committee.
Thank you. An important addition indeed.
Any other councilors have-- Councilor Coleman? Yes.
And that we have four representatives on the Metro board.
Yes.
So we're well represented.
We are. South Portland represent.
All right.
Now, do we have a roll call vote? Thank you.
Councilor Matthews?
Yeah.
Councilor West?
Yes.
Councilor Pride?
Councilor Coleman?
Yes.
Councilor Walker?
Councilor Scott?
Yes.
Mayor Tipton?
Yes. Thank you.
Okay. We are really rooting through them, and we have
reached number six, Order 187.
Please read that for us.
Of course. Order 187-25-26, Adopting the South Portland
Comprehensive Plan. Passage requires majority vote and again, this will be a roll
call vote.
Thank you. So I'll just explain that we have
this organized in the following way.
We're going to have some brief introductory remarks by our
city manager, then we're going to hear some remarks
from the chair of our Comprehensive Planning Committee,
Howard Kunin,
and then Milan, our planning director, Milan
Nevada, will present what he has prepared for us
to understand the comprehensive plan,
at least at a fairly high level.
And then we'll have time for council questions, then we'll have
public comment, and then we'll have a council discussion and
see if that leads us to a vote.
That's the plan, ladies and gentlemen. Thank you for being with us.
City manager, please.
Thank you, Mayor. I don't have much to say.
I just wanted to
start
briefly by mentioning that
as the Comprehensive Plan Committee has wrapped up its work, they voted to send you
now a final draft of their updated comprehensive plan,
and now under law, it's up to the elected officials of the community
to pass the plan in order for it to become
effective. Milan and Howard will
talk
extensively about what's in the plan.
Even though I know a lot of folks have already read it and provided
informed comments on the plan.
Before I turn it over to
Howard to do some introductory remarks of his own, I just want to thank
several entities, including the committee itself,
the staff that staffs the committee and has also provided input,
and then the public for showing up at all of these meetings and
providing extensive input in person and via email, and
things of that nature. I've been working in various capacities in municipal
government for over 20 years now. Comp plans don't come up that
often, so I've only lived through really two different processes, this one and
another.
But in talking to other colleagues, I don't know any process that's gone on
for over really a year, and this one has gone on, we're entering
year four, and so that's just a lot of time and energy for the
staff, for the committee members, for members of the public to stay engaged,
and I think that deserves some
kudos,
especially on the committee's end for all the time that they've spent on getting
this document to where it is. So thank you to the committee, thank you
staff and members of the public for showing up.
Now I'm going to turn it over to the comp plan chair, Howard Kunin, to provide
some remarks.
Thank you, Scott.
So I'm Howard Kunin. I live on Walnut Street.
I'm the District 2 representative and the current chair of the comp
plan.
I want to begin by acknowledging and thanking everyone who served on the committee,
and
of course, the current members.
That includes Kathleen Egan,
Bob Foster,
Mike Hulsey,
Anne Jordan,
Jennifer Kinney, Jeff McDonald, Christopher Paine,
Marty Reel,
Peter Stanton,
Pedro Vazquez,
Mayor Tipton, and Councilor West.
I want to thank them for all their-
Get the mic.
Excuse me?
Get closer to the mic.
Okay.
How's that?
Yeah.
All right. So I want to thank them all for their time, their hard work, and their
dedication to the plan. Several of these members have been on the committee since
it was established more than three years ago.
I also want to particularly acknowledge Peter and Kathleen for their
dedicated service as previous chairs of the committee.
And on behalf of the committee, we want to thank Milan and Eli Rubin for
supporting this process with their expertise, their skill, and
especially their patience.
The committee would also like to acknowledge and thank the many members of the
public who participated in outreach efforts, attended committee
meetings,
contributed oral and written comments, and provided online
input to the completed plan draft.
The majority of the policy guidance in the plan was reached either through
consensus or by solid majority vote,
and I think it's fair to say that the majority of this policy guidance
also seems to have good community consensus.
The area that we struggled with, as you all know, is the
eastern waterfront. So I just want to speak briefly to
that.The policies that we are recommending for CALUPA
21, the Eastern Waterfront coastal area, and
CALUPA 22, the shipyard and terminal area,
are attempting to balance the city's goals of climate resilience,
protecting public health,
promoting balanced growth,
and increasing housing.
We were also mindful that the property covered by these policies is
privately owned.
We heard the public's valid concerns about sea level rise,
oil tank emissions,
level of development, and traffic.
We share those concerns, and we try to address them through policies that
include, for example, accounting for 8.8 feet
of sea level rise for public and private critical infrastructure,
which can be found in core theme 1A.2 on page 15 of the plan.
Incorporating the coastal resilience overlay zone, which is referenced in
multiple places.
Conditioning new residential development on evidence-based studies
by a credible scientific source that considers both current and
potential VOC emissions impact on health,
and considering the adoption of residential land use separation standards.
Both of these are in core theme 5C.14
on page 37, and in CALUPA 22 strategy B
on page 108.
And also then adopting development standards that will minimize increase
in congestion along Broadway,
which is strategy J9 on page 109 of CALUPA 22.
There was intense and thoughtful debate among committee members while we worked
on these policies,
and we certainly recognize and respect that there are members of the public who
don't agree with the approach that we are proposing for the Eastern Waterfront.
But at the end of the process, the plan that we are presenting to you for your
consideration reflects our best effort at contributing to the
positive future of South Portland in the Eastern
Waterfront and indeed across the city.
I'll be available to answer any questions as you have your deliberations.
So, thank you.
Thank you very much, Howard, and thank you for serving as the
committee chair.
I'm not sure who has the control for the projection in the back.
Once again, Milan Nevida, the planning director.
Just as that's coming up, I
had several words, but most of them have already been said.
So I just want to echo my thanks to Howard and the prior chairs, Kathy and
Peter, and all the members of the committee.
I also want to specifically call out Eli Rubin, our community planner, who
really led the planning effort for the last year and a half,
making sure that we're getting through the large volume of both research
that's required to present the packets, and then also the content that goes into
each one of the CPC meetings.
Specifically on that, and this is some of the stuff that we don't necessarily get
to showcase,
I do want to call out Eli for
some of the hard work that he put in on the engagement side of things.
As Scott was mentioning, this has been a long four-year process, and one of the
key reasons why it's taken that amount of time is because we wanted to design a
process that allowed people to communicate with us and weigh in,
and weigh in in multiple ways, and also to do it within a span of time that
seemed reasonable. There were four or five times through this process that
we pushed out the comment period by two, three months or four months or five
months, to just give that space because this is such
an important milestone for the community and sets us up for a very long
time. One of the things that Eli, I think, really
emphasized and put energy towards, and I think helped in this plan, is
reaching out to specific target groups and trying to understand what their
perspectives were, folks that don't typically come out.
So coming and having meetings with
South Portland high school kids, organizations that work throughout the region to
represent minority groups,
working alongside folks that are able to translate to meet with minority
populations that don't have the voice even to speak in the way that we would
normally understand it, to just try and solicit as much public input as we
possibly could from both the folks that can come out comfortably and do
so routinely, but also for everybody else.
I think that was an important
amount of time spent, and I really do think it is reflected in the plan.
And so I want to call out his efforts there.
I also want to thank our city manager's office for supporting this
through the budget process and the city council for providing us the funding to
do this work, but also all my department head peers
and colleagues and all of their staff because this plan was vetted at
multiple stages through your technical staff members to advise on
whether these things that we've included on the pages here are feasible,
are responsive to what they're seeing on the ground, are real,
and to inform how we can do them and where we can get the funding to do them
and what creative ways we can approach some of these problems
with. So this is not a plan represented just by even the
CPC and planning, even though we certainly spent the more focused time
on it, but everyone has weighed in, and I hope this is resonating
in what's on the page.
Milan, hang on for just one second.
Can people hear Milan?
Not really.
Milan, we've noticed that this microphone requires you to practically
eat it sometimes. So you really have to lean in.
Okay.
Thank you.
Is this better?
Yes.
All right.
It'll almost be better.
Big thanks to everybody.
So
this council received the bulk of this plan
back in June of 2025.
Right.
So I wanted to focus the presentation just on what's changed
since then.And highlight some of the key things, and then
as Chair Coonan had emphasized, obviously go into a
little bit more detail on that Eastern Waterfront area, just because the policy
approach there was just so nuanced and delicate to try and find
a balance between everything that we had been hearing.
So there'll be a little background, primarily overview of our plan changes,
and then just a reminder again on what we're seeking from council tonight, which is
a decision on where to go next.
We obviously worked carefully with the Comp Plan committee.
I just want to call out one more time that the Comp Plan committee is both the
council's committee, but it's also the committee recognized by the state to perform
the act of preparing a comprehensive plan and making a recommendation to you.
So it does wield that responsibility.
And I'm happy to report, as you have in your packet, that the
state
has found the committee's plan consistent.
In the final slides, I will go over a little bit of process,
and one of those procedural steps is that we do need to send this back to the state
for recertification because there have been refinements.
Any changes have to go back to the state.
But in communication with them, all of the changes that the CPC and perhaps
the council will introduce have proposed they don't
really interact with anything that the state cares about.
They're local policies, things like what are we doing with the Eastern Waterfront.
The state sets larger state policies, and
so the recertification is not a concern of ours,
and we
expect that we will be able to get recertified pending your guidance, obviously.
This plan includes everything that the Comp Plan is supposed to include.
But again, it also goes beyond that.
What's been clear from the get-go when we engage with the community is that there
are elements of the plan that
don't get addressed by the state requirements, and we want to
address them as a community. Those specifically are our policies related to health
and well-being, social vitality, sustainability and climate action, and
education. These don't appear on the state's checklist, but they're
important to us and they have been included.
I'm quite proud that we were able to dedicate the time to do that.
We began this in 2021. We began with a sort of forensic analysis on
how we've been doing with land use planning so far and the policies of 2012.
This is a picture of an audit that we did of that plan.
And then we engaged with the community, as I've mentioned a few times.
Organizations, individuals, met them where they are, invited them
into hosted curated meetings, workshops, walk shops,
all manner of things.
So far, the CPC has met on 64 occasions in formal meetings,
with the staff attending an additional 23 meetings with other committees.
And as of today, we've received about 450 written comments that
have all been posted to CPC agendas and made available to the committee so that
they can deliberate as they consider the next policy step.
And in our final round of communications after engagement, after
your June workshop,
we continued that model. We added in a new interactive
tool when we prepared that preliminary draft plan to have the community weigh in
on it in real time. I think some of you engaged with it.
You can digitally read the plan, submit your comments, see what your neighbors
submitted, riff on that, add to that, like what they said, emphasize
it, and so on. We had 688 submissions come through and a
ton of content that the committee digested one by one and
addressed each issue that was raised.
When you last saw this plan, it was what we call a preliminary
draft plan. We wanted to get your input on key
questions, and you gave us the go ahead with some guidance.
You're now seeing the final draft plan, and it is, if you accept it,
ready for adoption as written, but can still be
modified. So this is still very much an open process.
I think you're familiar with the structure of the plan.
It works through our goals and strategies.
It's expressed spatially on a map called the Future Land Use
plan.
And it includes what's unique to South Portland, these key land use policy areas,
KLUPAs.
Our goals and strategies are expressed through six key themes.
But since June, we've added a seventh one, and it's a little bit of a housekeeping
administrative one. This is just a shell for all of the
required state policies. Many of them are redundant and overlap
substantially with policies we've adopted at the local level through themes one
through six. But in order to make sure that we can easily pass
the certification step, we also included the high-level required
policies, and that's what theme seven is about.
I just want to call that out because again, you did not see that last time.
These are state required.
This is what your future land use map looks like today.
It's very similar to what you saw last time.
We changed the colors and graphics a little bit for some ADA.
We ran it through an ADA accessibility reader test and made some
refinements to make sure we were accounting for that.
That's why color-wise, it's quite different.
But there are a handful of adjustments I do want to call out in what
you saw last. First, we did not formally designate at the
time in June what was happening outside of the key land use policy areas.
We knew generally what the policy intent was.
The future land use plan with the CPC's guidance has now cemented that.
All of those areas you see in this plan with an X are outside
of key land use policy areas. We expected that those areas would
continue to contribute to the community in the way that they already
are. So just do more of the same.
And since we last saw you, we've now formalized that guidance and given it a
limited growth designation, and this is the kind of growth where we're looking for
infill development similar to what's there.
So that's a small tweak, but an important one just to clarify what's happening in
the voids between KLUPAs.
Obviously, we've done
considerable work within the Eastern Waterfront.
I have dedicated slides to that, so we'll get back to that
one.The Pleasantdale coastal area.
Staff missed a bit on this one. We had a clear, I think,
policy intent. I think the CPC read what our policy intent was, but the way we
expressed the policies just got muddled when the community
read it. And so we had to make some really simple but important
distinctions to be clear about what we were doing in Pleasantdale, and it was to
protect the single-family neighbors that are there, but also
create some incentives so Broadway properties can do more for coastal resilience.
So that was an important refinement.
And then we did do some boundary adjustments here.
There's a large commercial property, the former Aetna building, that we formerly
put into CALUPA 1, which is a residential-focused CALUPA, and we
moved it to CALUPA 2, which is a commercial-focused CALUPA.
So, a few adjustments there. This is what our
CALUPAs look like when you open them up on the page.
It's a little different than what you saw last time, but generally very
similar. It has all those elements that tell you what you're looking at.
One thing that's been introduced since we last saw you is that we now set a
preferred scale for the height and density
of development within that area. That's residential density.
So if the committee felt it was important
for this area to have some form of a benchmark, to some form of a number
to help identify what a certain policy statement might be, like when we
say moderate growth, what does that mean?
Well, in some CALUPAs, it's really sensitive.
And so we took the time to insert those guidance posts there.
And then, of course, there's been refinements through the language all throughout.
But that scale preference piece was an important addition, and we've
gone through each CALUPA and
addressed that.
All right. Major revisions since June,
starting with the Eastern Waterfront.
This is the map that you saw
back at your workshop. We divided the Eastern Waterfront into two areas.
They're labeled one and two there, light and dark green.
The kind of organizing principle at the time was that we look at
the tank properties or tank-held properties as one
thing because they needed focus guidance, and then the other
more development-ready
areas as something else.
And then created a whole policy framework on that.
As a quick reminder, area one, I think that number was
14 at the time that we presented it to you.
It was meant to be those tank areas.
It was supposed to follow what happens in the other
area once those tanks were gone. So it just sort of deferred to
the second one.
And some of the key pieces in there was that it would have to be scaled down.
So it had single-family neighbors. It had to ratchet down.
It had to be substantially set back from the water, any development.
Residential was not allowed near the water.
Greenbelt needed to be expanded, and we were supposed to track and reduce
emissions. Those are some of the high-level key focal points for area
one. And area two
allowed a mix of uses, was able to reach up to six stories,
focused on pedestrian scale, required contamination cleanup,
connected open spaces need to be provided that build on,
expand Bug Light, and also become available for the neighbors.
Freight traffic had to be avoided.
Traffic needed to avoid Ferry Village and not connect to Ferry Village.
That's a 2012 policy that was still there back in June.
It needed to provide access to the waterfront.
Peak hour traffic on Broadway needed to be limited.
The street network had to be connected. Transit had to be supported.
We need to provide a mix of housing types and the forested area near Bug
Light that we all read as Bug Light
would
be acquired hopefully, or we would put energy towards acquiring it.
This is the map that's before you today.
We have two CALUPAs, 21 and 22,
and I'm just showing there Bug Light, which is in a separate CALUPA, always has
been, and that's 23. All the formal city property is
separated out.
I'm going to just highlight the key
approaches now that we have with CALUPA 21 and 22.
In 21,
this is now not a tank-oriented CALUPA.
It's focused on what we're doing in the coastal area.
One of the sticking points was that we had this policy that says
residential needs to be set back from the water, trying to respond to some of the
concerns around sea level rise, flooding,
and so on.
But it was always difficult with the committee to address, well, what do we mean by
set back? Is it 10 feet? Is it 5,000 feet?
Is it something in between? What's the appropriate number?
Comp plans are supposed to be guidance.
So it's not
common to have something so specific prescribed in here, but we wanted to give
better definition to it. So by changing the boundaries and saying, "Let's be more
specific about what we want near the water because that's clearly a sensitivity,
and then let's look at inland upland property a little bit differently," that
helped drive how we drew the boundaries.
In those areas closest to the water, we ratcheted the
heights down from six stories to three stories.
We added policies around preserving public views.
We stated that open spaces had to be maximized, not just
provided. Stormwater had to be retained, and space had to be
relegated for the stormwater retention as well as coastal
buffering from the storms and flooding.
And we had to connect to rather than avoid Ferry Village and
fight this
prior policy of creating an enclave.
We wanted it to be, if it was going to be developed, be developed
contiguous with and connected with and
benefiting the surrounding neighborhoods, not separate and apart from.
21B
is a sub-area. There's two in there, A and B.
21B is over by the Portland Terminal and that forested area of Bug
Light. It allows a much more restricted
number of land uses because it says that only land uses that
are water-dependent can exist there, so water-dependent forms of
retail, water-dependent forms of marine uses, and so
on.And then we've always had this policy of expanding the green
belt, but we've added specific guidance around dedicating shoreline
trail access, wraparound access, and through access.
That's all contained in the new Area 21.
The points here I won't emphasize.
They're just things that we continue to maintain.
It's not that they've been forgotten.
So things about tracking VOCs, cleaning up contaminants,
expanding Bug Light Park, all of that has been retained.
I just want to highlight the things that are sort of unique and try to address
the concerns we were hearing.
In Area 22, the inland upland portions of the Eastern Waterfront,
there are four sub-designations, A, B, C, and D, and
generally, that gave us a policy framework so we could
change what's happening and what we allow to happen closest to
the water, and as we move further upland where it starts to get more closely
resilient,
we can allow more.
So 22A and 22D
also interact with the tanks. And so they have a specific provision
in there about assessing VOC risks.
This applies citywide, but we emphasize it again here.
And I think the important language that we use is that residential can be
considered. It is not an automatic allowance.
Zoning has to happen with any of the recommendations in this plan,
but there is no requirement to allow residential.
The city council has to be sufficiently convinced that it's appropriate
when it designates zoning in order to make that possible.
So this is just saying what conversations can be had and not
opening up residential upon plan adoption.
And I have some procedure steps later on that we'll touch on.
As the plan moves inland upland,
the sub-areas A, B, C, and D ratchet up in scale.
Closest to the water, it maintains that three-story height limit,
and then as you get to 22C, it can allow up to five stories, and
22D, which
currently has those two tanks, but also the vacant property that abuts Broadway,
can reach up to six stories, and that was to parallel what we see at Betsy Ross.
Additions to 22 that are important
is that bike ped improvements have to be provided, and they have to be provided by
a developer at the time of development.
Public views must be maintained, and importantly in
22, because much of this area does not provide a view
for the public from a public vantage point, they have to be newly
created for the first time. The open spaces need to be
maximized. We are targeting clean energy sector additions out here
because there was a desire to see some industrial heritage maintained,
but we want to do it in a more benign and more residential compatible way for the
neighbors nearby.
Coastal resilience is emphasized at the terminals, and we'd work in
concert with Maine DEP, the Department of Environmental Protection,
or even at the local level to ensure that those properties
are resilient to coastal storms. We, again, would
rather connect to than avoid Ferry Village and expand
the green belt as well as that shoreline trail.
The text in blue are all those additions.
And again, the other familiar language from June is still in
here, controlling for Broadway traffic, contamination cleanup, VOC
tracking, et cetera.
I want to now speak in a little bit more plain terms rather than policy terms on
what success looks like based on the policies that are written on
this page for the Eastern Waterfront on some
major topics, traffic and three others.
On traffic, this plan asks for limited
new freight traffic on Broadway. It will be a transit-supportive
form of development. It will be connected streets and avoid an
enclave. Broadway will be familiar to what we know today.
Bug Light access will be improved, enhanced, and made better
in all possible ways. Bike ped access will be
substantially better. Housing will be
diversified, not purely luxury, set back,
and flood resilient, human scaled.
It will be inland and upland. It will be connected to and
compatible with surrounding neighborhoods.
On coastal resilience, the plan will only accept
development that is responsive to the best available data, that
leans on the cross, but then tracks new science and gets updated as
we learn more. Flood mitigation is promoted and required
in the way that land is used, and private developers have to
contribute to that process.
On open space recreation,
a minimum substantial area has to be reserved
even through private development.
At least 20 acres is easily required by the plan,
both in the conservation that's required over at the Bug Light adjacent area, the
coastal areas, the green belt expansions, the public
pathways that are required through here.
That is a minimum,
and certainly much, much more can be preserved and will depend on
the partners that we strike, including nonprofits that may
develop and acquire that land.
The green belt will be widened, extended, provide more
features, provide more views, provide access to more
places. Bug Light will be expanded and
sheltered from development or any adjacent development that may
detract from what Bug Light is today.
The open spaces will be woven into any development that has to
come forward, not relegated as side thoughts at the time of
development. And the Portland Street Pier property that the city manages
will be supported and potentially finally have access to parking so
that people can enjoy that benefit, whether the city's operating it or
other operators are operating
it.Shifting to other
areas of the plan that were changed.
We spent some time refining, as I mentioned, those scale
preferences. When we published those, we heard feedback and we made
further refinements, specifically on height and density preferences.
We spent a little more time being delicate in areas like Mill Creek,
where we have the letter streets and the more
like the Knightville areas, which are smaller scale, but then also the concept
of our downtown wanting to provide opportunities.
So right now, Mill Creek advocates for six stories.
It's potentially able to reach up to eight stories, but it requires a
high-quality design proposal, and we would articulate what that is
through the zoning framework. Our Nutter Hill inland tank farm,
which has had significant community conversation.
We learned from the community meetings and the thoughts shared through
that effort. The Toss the Tanks folks were coming to many of our
meetings,
and we tried to reflect scale that we saw in the plan.
Notably, five stories within the core seems reasonable,
but it must taper and blend into the single-family neighborhoods around
in order for it to be a successful and acceptable kind of development.
And then over at the Sable Oaks area, we received, I think, some really
interesting technical feedback from folks that
have explored development out there that shed more detail on
the development constraints because of ledge, because of wetlands, because of
natural resources, and we responded by saying we still want to
strive for that 20 units per acre. That is still our preference.
But when we learn more details, technical details, geotechnical
details, we will develop ordinances that allow us to have an
intelligent conversation understanding those constraints and when they might
get
in the way of specifically that number in the plan.
Corridors have been something that we talked about very
early in the plan process and always understood as something we wanted to
incorporate in this plan.
But they got somewhat muted as we kept developing the
policies. One of the refinements we made was to adopt
a specific provision that just tied a
bow around policies that we have been saying but not quite
articulating, and that is that all areas of the community are going to need to
contribute to housing in a way that's comfortable for what that area is.
Some areas are comfortable for more levels of growth than others.
I talked earlier about our non-CA LUPA areas, which should just continue
to be like what they already are, but provide some infill opportunities.
Wherever we land with the density designations throughout town, the
corridors are expected to get a little oomph.
They should be able to do a little more and provide a little bit more diversity and
a little bit more flexibility. We're not talking going from two stories and then
suddenly on a corridor you're at 10 stories, but the concept of the
corridors can do a little bit more.
And this is to try and reinforce the
transit-oriented development that we need to see in our community to try and
provide for our transit goals in the long term, but also where
we see infrastructure and the potential to develop
without disrupting neighborhoods.
I talked a little bit about Pleasantdale coastal area.
This is a technical correction, but it's important because we had some very
specific comments come back from neighbors concerned, and I want to clarify it in
case they're here tonight.
The policy for Pleasantdale was always a level B
designation of growth, which is just consistent with what it already is.
What we were trying to achieve and what I think the policy now clearly states is
that Broadway has the potential for the back lots
behind these fronting properties to do more for
coastal resilience by allowing inundation area.
And we would try to encourage those Broadway property owners to provide that
benefit by allowing more development flexibility closer to the street,
to try and bring structures and pavement closer to the street and
have open space in the back that can serve as that buffer.
And so I think we just tried to clear up the language on that, but it was no
different in the intent from what you saw in June, just better language.
This slide has a lot on it. I will come back to it if there's council questions.
I'm sure questions will come up from the public.
Air quality and handling the VOC emissions
tracking is an important consideration throughout this plan.
We have citywide policies to mind this issue
across the entire city, but we also have CA LUPA policies specifically
where we know it's a sensitivity.
There are three key things that we're doing.
Howard, our chair, emphasized them here.
I just want to highlight the headlines here, but we have specific references to, I
think, relevant policy on this issue.
Number one, we are supporting in any possible way the
transition of the tank terminals into something that's an
alternative, cleaner, better, more compatible form of development.
That's a general policy, and there are many
kind of nuanced policies that try to get at that.
Some of them are listed here. The second major thread here is
that we are committing to tracking,
evaluating, overall reducing VOCs, and that
we are not allowing new residential until the city council is
sufficiently satisfied that the VOC emission risks
are insignificant and it is
appropriate to allow development next to them, but only then can
residential be considered.
And then we do have kind of related contamination
cleanup policies throughout the plan to make sure that any
existing contaminants are not evaporating and causing air
quality or other contamination concerns to our waterways.
Three other major amendments that we integrated since
June.
Civic facilities. TheCouncil has been engaged in a pretty
heavy conversation about what the future of our city facilities are.
And what we realize is that the plan, in some cases, largely pulling from
the 2012 plan, was maybe a little too prescriptive in where
we expected those solutions to come about.
So one thing we did is we built in maximum flexibility
for the city council with the community to
designate where it wants to provide civic services and how it
wants to provide those. And if CALUPAs were involved, they also echoed that
language. We are trying to give, again, maximum flexibility so that we can
do the best thing for the community for the long term with locating civic
facilities. On open space and resilience, we
introduced policy 1C19. The intent of
this policy is to give council the best possible negotiating
position to secure open space and coastal
resilience commitments
from development,
and to make sure that they contribute to that process.
And then finally, this is a bit of a wonky piece in our new
policies.
This planning office, together with the economic development office, has been
working on a number of streamlining measures to help development move along.
One of those is to look at absorbing state-level review for
environmental impacts in the planning department.
This is called delegated authority.
MDEP would allow us to do the review for them.
This requires some research and some work, and eventually a presentation
to the city council, and discussions with the city manager and others on things
like staffing capacity and so on. But if it is the right decision
for the city of South Portland, it will require a statement
in the plan that we are okay going that route.
And so we've included the state-required verbatim language that
just says, "If we're ready to make the decision, here's the policy that would
support that decision. If we never make the decision, we're not obligated, and we
keep doing what we're doing." But we just needed this in there, otherwise you'd
have to amend the plan later if it was the smart thing for us to be doing.
Okay. On comp plan implementation, I just want to walk
us through, briefly, process. This is important.
As we've been going through this long-range planning effort, we often hear
comments, I'm sure you may hear some tonight,
reacting to a policy statement on the page and a reality
that that's going to create tomorrow.
And that's unfortunately just not how it works.
It takes a long time for the policy to become
anything that can be realized. We are at this stage, the comp plan
adoption stage. If you accept it, it would be adopted by the council
tonight. We'd send it for certification with the state, and I'm confident
we would receive that.
Once the comp plan actually gives us direction through the adopted plan,
we then go through mostly a zoning process, but there are many
other processes that will have to take place with the non-land use provisions
that are in this policy. On just land use,
allowing residential in certain areas, for instance, changing the density, changing
the heights allowed.
We need time to develop that zoning.
The comprehensive plan committee will presumably be involved
in more of the significant ones, but the council will direct us to work with
committees if it wants to.
At a minimum, though, the planning board will have to review any zoning proposals.
They do that at a planning board hearing.
And that will be presented to council eventually through two ordinance adoptions,
and a super majority is needed for zoning amendments, not just
four. At the time that any zoning is presented, and I'll
touch on the sensitive topic I'm sure you've already heard and will hear
more about tonight is the allowance of residential near industrial
areas. The council needs to evaluate whether that zoning
proposal includes
policies that are consistent with the plan,
and that those policies are responding to
what information we have available, and is the information that we have available
complete.
Are the VOC studies complete, and does the plan include the controls that
respond to the data that we've received?
What is the state of the tank farms? Are they operating? Are they operating at max?
Are they operating with the potential to increase?
What is the coastal flooding modeling telling us?
What is the CROZ doing, and is it performing?
Are the developments that we've seen with the CROZ, Coastal Resilience Overlay
Zone, working? And is the CROZ still
effective five years out as new models come about?
What are the market conditions, and of course, what does the rest of the
comprehensive plan say, and is this zoning proposal
consistent?
We expect over the next three years to be working on zoning.
Even when zoning is adopted,
it takes time for a development proposal to be drafted that is
reflective of that zoning.
We would expect there to be a lag after the zoning is adopted
before we ever entertain any formal development proposal, and then that goes
through development review.
At the time of development review, based on the specific development in the
specific location at the specific scale and the specific mix of
uses that's proposed, we will be looking at what are the traffic impacts,
if any. What is the lot plan and layout, and how does that marry
up with the standards of the plan and the standards of the zoning ordinance that
implement the plan? Are the elevations that are proposed
consistent with where we expect them to be for that type of building and for
that type of use?
Is the view that's supposed to be preserved actually preserved?
And so on and so forth. Development typically takes
two to three years beyond the point when they've actually received their
approval. So we need to understand all of these
steps and layers to doing the checks and balances to make the
policy something that's real and something that takes
shape on the land.I want to speak a little
bit to comp plan implementation, because this is a multiple
hundred-page document. It includes appendices, it includes
background information, and as we learned through the comprehensive plan audit of
the 2012 plan, not everything got implemented.
Our approach, and we're still developing this, so you will see this over the
next year if the plan is adopted,
is to continue working with the comprehensive plan committee, which is going to
shift into implementation mode.
The planning division is primarily administering the plan,
but every one of these policies in here includes a responsible
party who's responsible for reporting on progress made to that
plan.
So the CPC is a key
actor in making sure that we're making progress, the planning division, and of
course, the city manager and city council.
The CPC is going to receive staff reports regularly as
it meets on how we're doing with progress.
They will, as a first step in the fall, be working on a work plan
that takes that timeframe column of when we expect each policy to be
implemented and move it into an action plan.
So these policies don't necessarily express exactly what's going to be
done in order to make the policy happen.
The work plan with the CPC will do that, and it will be informed
by feedback from the department heads.
The CPC does annual reporting to the council, and it holds public
meetings. The planning division does annual reporting, and we intend to
stand up a website that will track the status of our policies and
whether we've achieved them, are they're in progress, how far along are they, and
so on.
And then, of course, the city manager and the council process includes annual goal
setting, where I expect we'll be having some conversations about where's the right
place to put emphasis in that given year.
And then, of course, our budget and CIP process will reflect the initiatives that
we want to kick off, especially when they require funding.
Every other department also requires an annual report and
will share their thoughts on initiatives they have on the go.
So tonight, I think what we've presented to the council for consideration
is a balanced plan that responds to your
June 2025 feedback,
that responds to the community feedback that we've heard, that puts checks
and balances in the appropriate places where we're sensitive, but
also allows us to reach and strive for the things that we want to go after in the
next 15 years. The council's options tonight, I think as the
city manager's covered in his position paper, are to
adopt, adopt with revisions, continue the meeting
with amendments or guidance for amendments, and certainly the CPC is
available if there are more complex topics to tackle to come back
to you
with more refined language.
I'm happy to take any questions and dive deeper into any of these
topics, but I think I'll stop it there.
Thank you.
Did you want to say something?
I'm just going to wrap things up. Yeah.
So thanks, Milan. So those are the council options.
Thanks for covering those, Milan.
Staff does recommend adoption of the plan.
We do have, and we've provided input throughout the process about
some things that
we'd rather maybe see tweaked or not in there or
that didn't make it in there. But we also, at this point, respect the
process that things have gone through, and so we do recommend council approval.
But you have those four options here tonight
in front of you,
ranging from if you feel a plan can be adopted as is all the way
to it's nowhere near close to ready, so send it back to the committee to do more
sausage making.
Okay. Thank you very much, Scott. Thank you,
Milan. And I was going to say we're going to move to
council questions. So Councilor Pride, looks like you're starting
us off.
Thank you. And Milan, thank you for that great presentation.
And Chair Kunin, thank you for those thanks to all the
people, because it sounds like a lot of work went into this plan.
In fact, I know a lot of work went into this plan.
But I will start with questions, starting with maybe the one nearest
dearest to my heart, probably the most important question.
For K Lupa 16, if the Hearts of Pine were to purchase the Hill Street
tank farm, would they be allowed under this plan to build their stadium
there so that I could walk to games?
We can look up the K Lupas policy specifically.
I have them up.
That area does allow and really focuses on
residential, but it does allow compatible types of activities.
So recreational indoor soccer field would be allowed.
But a large scale commercial soccer facility end to
end would not be supported. It would have to be a neighborhood.
Okay. Might have to make a change there.
So bringing us back to reality,
K Lupa 22 and 23, I know a
lot of people have that on their mind.
Would the comprehensive plan as written, keep the
city from designating a buffer zone between the
Bug Light Park and further into those K Lupas
as park
zone?
No. The policies would be supportive of that approach if you wanted to see it
through zoning.
Does it need to be in the comprehensive plan for the city to do that?
No.
Would you-
Well, it is in the plan.
Right. Okay.
Yeah.
Fair.
Would you expect to see something like that in a comprehensive plan if there was
a serious effort to do that?
So we
presented a matrix to the comprehensive plan committee, I think two
meetings ago,
two of their meetings ago.And what the matrix tried to do,
maybe it was a little earlier than that, actually.
What the matrix tried to do was lay out the policy options for some of the
community conversations that were happening.
And at the time, we understood groups like SOS were exploring
an open space acquisition out there, a substantial one.
And that's admirable goal. Virtually all of their
goals are supported by the policies in this plan.
The one area where the plan would have a
limitation is if the expectation was that
the city was purchasing all of the property in K
LUPA 21 and 22. At that point,
that's an action of the city council that would undermine some of the other goals
that were put into K LUPA 21 and 22. And so our
process when the city is contemplating acquisition is that you consult
with the Open Space Acquisition Committee and the Planning Board.
The Planning Board's role is to tell you whether there's policy in the plan
that does not support us acquiring open space
there. And I would suspect the Planning Board would say
100% acquisition from everywhere by the city for a city
park is not striking the balance that this plan calls for.
So save that one scenario of total
park acquisition everywhere,
all other versions of it are possible.
And if it was a private party buying all of the
land and keeping it as a park, whether it's a nonprofit or some other
partnership, they could do that
all day long because it's private property, and they can just keep it as park and
allow public access. But it would have to be just that city
purchase scenario.
I guess my question is, generally speaking, do you see
that kind of granularity in a
comprehensive plan in general? If a city is looking
at creating a buffer like that or a park that's a part of a K LUPA
or whatever they call them in other comp plans,
do they generally have that plan sketched right out in detail in the comp
plan?
Yes and no. The no is relevant to our context.
South Portland, complex community, multiple things going on,
multiple issues to tackle. It's not common for
us to be writing a site plan for an open space acquisition
within a comp plan. But where in Maine, most comp plans
are handling small communities where literally all they're doing for the
next 10 years is trying to purchase that little piece of city forest, and
that's what they spend all their time talking about, and it's important to them.
So if you
took all the comp plans in the main, you probably would find several that talk
specifically about one land acquisition from one family, and that's important.
But for us, for our context, for what we're trying to balance and manage,
no.
Okay. And maybe for communities of similar size doing similar kind of
planning?
Yeah.
The other piece that I really want to-- and there's a few more questions,
so I apologize, councilors. But with the
methodology by which any given developer were to
suggest residential and then have to figure out the health
impacts of VOCs and
if they're close to any kind of tank farm facility
or any tanks,
does the council get to prescribe that?
Could we make a zoning
amendment that states that
any developer would have to submit their
data or allow the Sierra Club to come in,
collect their sample, send it to a lab that the Sierra Club trusted,
and then the Sierra Club would report to us whether
they would be allowed to develop residential in the area.
Could we create a zoning amendment like that?
Yes, you can create a zoning standard that
says in order to say yes to any development, the planning board has to
see
very prescriptive kinds of data. You can assign that yourself.
If you wanted to defer the issue of getting that data to the
private side of things, that's totally doable,
and we can certainly do that. Because the community has been doing so much with
data collection and analyzing it on our own,
the assumption here is that we would be learning from that and then presenting
the city council with data, yay or nay.
This feels like we have enough to say it's safe, and therefore you're seeing
an ordinance that allows residential, or we don't have enough
staff at this point is not in a position of saying, "You clearly have an option
to approve this," or we see a scenario where council can make the
finding. So you can approach it any way you want.
The one thing you are certainly protected from is a developer coming forward
and saying, "There's policy. It says residential is okay
here, and here's a study from whatever saying
the VOCs are not a concern."
Council is not obligated, has no requirement
whatsoever to accept a residential proposal, whether it's from staff
or whether it's from a state agency or whether it's from a private developer.
And you set the terms on what is acceptable for you to make the finding, and
five of you have to do that, not your normal majority.
And I guess one sort of really
60,000 foot view question, sort of in relation to that,
if say that we put in the comp plan or the comp plan was accepted by council
saying, "No residential development here," would that
restrict a council from coming in and rezoning and saying, "You know what?
We actually do want residential here"?
One council cannot bind another council
just strictly through policy.
And that
rolls way back up. A future council can delete this comp plan and write a new
one and accept a whole new one with whole new policies.
That's technically possible.So it would be
doing measures like what you did, I think someone mentioned it in public comment,
amending the charter and putting in more checks and balances on certain things
that you want to protect. In those ways, you can establish a legacy.
But the
future council is the elected government of the people, and if they have a
different direction they want to take,
they have some opportunity to do that.
So in that vein where zoning requires a super majority to
change, changing the zoning after we've passed a comp plan would be the
better area to make change that was more difficult for a future council to
reverse?
More difficult and more specific. Yeah.
So for the last comp plan, we had several areas that
got master plans. Like Knightville got a master plan, Cash Corner got a
master plan. And so I noticed we kind of skipped the
master plan step on your timeline, because I know not everybody gets
one.
But master planning is part of the plan after the
comp plan is passed, correct?
For areas where, yeah, a master plan has a specific
role to play. For example, we call out master plans
in tank farm properties, where we don't see that the
applicant or property owner is wanting to do something different.
Maybe what we need to do is create a master plan and think
about all the barriers that they have and all the possible levers that the city
council and the city can move in order to encourage them in a different direction.
We need to spend some focus time dealing with that.
Just as an example, Main Mall is one we're looking at right now.
And what we're learning, one of the reasons why we haven't seen infill development
in the parking lot areas is because there's major infrastructure there and
huge geotechnical problems with the quality of the soil.
You just can't support buildings out there.
It's exorbitantly expensive to build at the mall.
And so one of the things we've advocated for, and you'll hear more about at the
time of the Texas Instruments TIF, for instance, is that maybe we can use some of
that money to focus master planning and try to understand those areas
better and maybe make some strategic investments to help the private market do
something that we want it to do. So master plans have that purpose, which allows us
to dive at a deeper level and understand and partner with people to better see
the conditions there.
Personally, I prefer master plans when they start to get at some of that
infrastructure problem, and really figure out what the solutions are, and
often those require investments or figuring out how we
combine investments and find sources of funding.
Not all areas need that. So it will be up to the
CPC and obviously the council.
We come to you through workshops and we'll say, "Look, I think we're ready for just
rezoning this area. We don't need to study X, Y, and Z.
But in this area, I think we need to get a master plan approach.
We can do it in-house. We need funding to do it if we need support," that kind of
thing. All those conversations would happen with you.
Yeah. So ultimately, the council could designate
a group of neighbors in the shipyard area to do a master plan for that
area that would also have an effect on zoning at a more granular level
than the comprehensive plan does.
So something like what we did with O'Neil Street, for instance, we created a
committee. It included community members in that vicinity to help
inform the vision, what kinds of things we were looking for that then
led to an RFP process and so on. So yeah, there's various ways that
the council can choose to form a body to be a sounding board or work with staff
or guide the process.
And all of that would be--
This comp plan obviously allows for all of that, the way that it's currently
stated.
Yeah. Yes.
All right.
That's all I have for questions. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Councilor Pride. Do we have more questions?
And also, I just want to remind folks who might accidentally be looking at that
clock, good news, it's 8:31.
Councilor Walker.
So I have a number of questions, but I'll just do a couple at a time, and so that
other people get a chance to ask their questions, too.
I'll start with two.
One is, ask them both, and you can decide which one you want to answer first.
One, I wanted to ask what happened with K Lupa 27.
Because it seems like it was something that solved for
many things, and I understand that it was the will of the Comp Plan committee for
it to go away, but if you could maybe talk a little bit about that.
And then my second one that I wanted to talk about
is K Lupa 1, or is it K Lupa 1?
It's the height requirements around at Main Mall, how there is no height
requirement around the Main Mall, and I just have some concerns about that, and
just wanted to talk about that, too.
Sure.
So K Lupa 27 was a
proposal that staff put together after we took a
little break from CPC meetings so that we could meet with individual CPC members
and try to understand how they were seeing the issues in that area.
And then we came back with what seemed to be
reflecting many of the things we heard, and then the CPC digested that
and considered it.
It led to what you see on the screen here,
and what's proposed tonight, the 21 and 22.
The big difference with K Lupa 27 is that we connected these two
kind of through this area, and in part, that was really looking at
distance from the water and adjacencies to Bug Light Park.
But apart from shifting the boundary to allow
more of this area, which is in common ownership, and also just
organized better in that sense,
I think K Lupa 27, a lot of it is reflected in the framework of
21 and 22.
But really, the K Lupa 22 Area B,
which is this one here, is the one where there was discussion about
what could that be, in part because it has that frontage on Madison.
It's the connection intoBug Light Park.
It already has buildings and development on it.
They've felt and moved it into more of the Kaloopa 22
framework.
Okay. Thank you.
And then the height. So,
this is one designation I think that it
was pretty
clean consensus all the way through when we were introducing that.
I think the
only way I would answer your question is to say that the committee, including
through public comment,
felt really bold about the mall and what it could do and what it
should be allowed to do, and the city did not want to establish height as
any barrier. One of the things we did at the mall and Sable Oaks
was say, not only
for the mall, the height can go unlimited, but we also established a minimum, not a
maximum density. And so one of the things that the committee, I think,
accepted or found comfortable was the idea that, well, look,
if we want them to strive for as much as possible,
why would we set up a scenario where maybe we say it's six stories, maybe we say
it's eight stories, and then someone needs eight stories plus a rooftop area that
the fire department would deem a story.
Or eight stories, but they need nine if they want to make the affordable
housing component viable. Or those geotechnical costs
are way higher than we anticipated, and again, they want to go just that
one story. So why establish height as an
overall limit? We did factor whether the airport would be a concern from
a safety perspective. It's not. It's too far away.
So really, I think the
committee felt that
development proposals are not going to be bringing on something that
is wild for the main context
out at the mall area. There are just some limitations just in the market
to getting something like that.
And we didn't have a lot of debate on that issue.
People felt pretty comfortable with it.
So I don't know that there's a scientific answer to why we picked that,
but those are some of the things that fed into it.
And so just to follow up with that, is there zoning that exists now
that needs to be changed for that Kaloopa, not just for the
height requirement, but for that Kaloopa in general?
Oh yeah, big time.
The 2012 plan wanted to protect the
mall and its vibrancy by
sheltering it from anything else.
And so the mall does not allow all of the things that today we
understand an evolving mall would need and want, and what frankly, the
mall owners have been talking to us about being very interested in.
It's just a little bit dated thinking.
And so we need to add residential. We need to modify parking
standards. We need to allow increased development
in bulk and form. So setbacks are really wide out there because the way they
viewed it is those major roads, we want volume
going through there, and we want nothing obstructing it.
And,
what that takes away is things like a high-quality
pedestrian environment. It's kind of hostile to pedestrians out there.
If you want to live out there, you're kind of living in an airport.
And so there's a variety of things that we need to revamp for the mall to start
feeling more like a mixed-use node.
And this isn't planners talking in a vacuum.
This is what we've been hearing from the development community as to what they
would feel is supportive of the type of direction they want to take.
Okay. And so much like your answer to Councilor Pride, if we wanted to put
some restraints on height, we could do that through zoning as we're moving through
this process.
Absolutely, yeah.
Thank you. And just Mayor would ask if we can
come back for more questions.
Yes. I think we should have a thorough amount of councilor
questions. We also would like to move to public
comment because we have a lot of members of the public here.
I don't think we can say that when we get to
council discussion that no councilor can ever ask a
question again. I think questions will also be allowed, but don't feel shy
right now. Other questions from councilors?
I don't see any on the left, and now I'll turn to the right.
Questions from councilors? I don't see.
Councilor Walker, I think you can continue then, and I have a
few myself.
Does Councilor Scott have any questions before I continue?
Oh, Councilor Scott. Hello.
Councilor Scott, do you have questions?
Not yet.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Okay.
All right, Councilor Walker.
I'm going to keep going then.
So in terms of the housing initiatives that are baked into the
comp plan in general, I know many of us are here to talk about the eastern
waterfront, but as a resident of the west side of the city, it is something that I
have been paying close attention to as well.
How do we ensure that growth isn't just made up of rental units?
So
what I mean by that is
I have grown concern over the last
little while when I think about the growth on the west side of the city, which is
where the majority of the community feels encouraged to put
growth. The growth over the last 10 years has been primarily rental units,
and so I worry about the dichotomy that we're setting up between the east side of
the city where home ownership is encouraged, and the west side of the city, if we
continue on this path, where it's primarily rental units.
So where in the housing initiatives and the comp
plan do we address things like that, or can we through the comp plan?
We certainly can.
So just because I have the map up here, the eastern waterfront has this policy, and
we move the same policy over into Sable Oaks,
and in the mall area, that housing has to be diverse.
It can't just be one type, one bedroom,
high quality luxury apartments for empty nesters or something like that,
which the market has ample desire
for.So diversity, and we don't
prescribe, because our housing report found that we have such
chronic and significant underproduction across the board, that it
makes no sense for us to be saying things like, "We need to really
amp up family-sized units."
Frankly, it's something I was looking for when we commissioned that study is, is
there a particular housing type that's just underserved, and do we need to help
it? And it's just grossly underserved in all categories.
So whatever we get is going to be really beneficial.
That's not to say that we can't set policy goals.
And we have done that in key land use policy areas.
We also have, in the housing theme, which applies
citywide, a statement to diversify housing.
We also have a statement to protect existing housing and protect existing
affordable housing. Something that we haven't really approached, for instance, is
the gentrification. As you invest in areas, whether it's for housing
or for non-residential development, wanting to protect the rents
and
the ability of existing homes to keep that affordable housing option available for
folks. So we have that baked into the plan.
When we get into the zoning for specific areas, if there's a
sensitivity in one area in particular, and I think your point is
valid about
new housing development really leaning onto the rental side because
it's done at scale, especially when we ask for 20 units per acre minimum,
are we only going to be getting apartments?
And so when we see the zoning for the main mall or for the
Sable Oaks area, that would be the time where we look to see those
things defined. Sable Oaks does have that diversification goal,
and the concept plans
that have already been put forward by the Sable Oaks developers, just as a proof of
what could go there and how it could get laid out, are a range of
apartments to cul-de-sac, single-family home type divisions.
So,
it's already looking at a range, and we can certainly reinforce that in policy.
Okay. Thank you.
Can I keep going?
Sure, please. You have good questions, and I think people are learning from them.
Okay.
So, in terms of the reduced parking requirements, how does that
play out with our winter parking ban?
And I'm thinking about specifically over the next two to four years.
So, we're talking about having one and a half
spaces or 0.75 spaces, and we want to kind of force the
reduction of cars.
Yeah.
But our transit environment does not support that yet.
So, how does the winter parking ban line up with that?
They have to come together. So we,
especially in more congested areas or more built-out areas like our
downtown,
we can't really eliminate the off-street parking
without having an actual solution to parking.
One way to approach it is to just remove the parking requirement, allow the
development to happen. It puts pressure on and makes things
uncomfortable, and then we get to a point where we want to fix that problem.
I think that's what you'll hear from the market, from the developers is, "We don't
really know that it's that bad. Let's just try it out, and we'll see it, and then
once you get the headaches, then we'll fix it."
We have no intention of approaching it that way.
I think we really need to understand all the mechanisms that are there.
I think our zoning ordinance absolutely has
a requirement of too much parking in certain scenarios.
And probably pretty easily, we already have the information, even
in our community, to say we just don't need that much parking.
If you look at things like the mall, where the ratio of parking required was
compliant 30 years, 40 years ago when it got built,
we definitely don't need that much, and we wouldn't put that number where it was
then today. So there's certain things we can do without a full-blown study and
without impacting the winter parking scenario.
But downtown Mill Creek, for instance, we can't touch parking until we have a
real solution on that. There is, I think, some
important analysis that has to be done about how we set up a
no winter parking ban scenario. I think that's
probably the lowest investment form of providing parking
to allow the whole area to become more of what the vision is.
But that's not to say it's an easy endeavor.
There's a lot of operational stuff we'll have to do.
We've had some conversations with our public works director.
We're talking different equipment, different scheduling, different police
pricing on illegal parking, parking enforcement in
general, possibly paid parking metering, and all the administration that goes
beside that. It's a fraction of the cost of building a garage and
just opening it up to folks.
But just because it costs less doesn't mean that it doesn't require
significant energy to make happen properly.
So we will have to take those two together.
Okay.
Just some technical... Sorry. Just some technical questions, and it sounds
like you may have answered this earlier.
With the timelines, the short, the medium, and the long-term timelines, is
that measured in years, months,
decade, next comp plan?
It's over the life of the plan, which is by state certification at 12 years.
So think of it in four-year chunks.
The work-
So we're at least one to four.
Yep.
Okay.
The work plan that the Comprehensive Plan Committee will define will actually put
some more refinement to it. It's worth mentioning again that
the plan is guidance. So, if something
appears in the medium range, but then it hops up as like a...
We've got a great opportunity to partner with something where the state's just made
a bunch of money available for a very particular kind of thing, but we happen to
have it in a long-term ordinance revision.
There's no reason why we can't move it up at your discretion.
Okay. I think I'll pause for now. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Councilor Welker.
Oh, Councilor Pride didn't apologize for asking questions. What the heck?Did too.
Oh, did you? Okay.
I will ask just a
couple of things because I think maybe it'd be helpful in advance of public comment
to get a little clarification. So,
on the matter of whether unique growth is high growth, we
do describe on page eight of this plan unique
high growth zones. And what I'm wondering is,
is that some sort of edit that needs to be made that they were originally
thought of as high growth zones before they got renamed
unique?
No. I think the section on page eight
is an executive summary. It's trying to distill-
Yes, I know that
... 100 pages into one.
And in this sense, we use the term unique high
growth
in talking the range of scales that's allowed.
So the specific policy is that CALUPAs can range from
a full conservation type CALUPA to something that
allows unique growth to what's there before, and also high growth.
But-
So I guess, Milan, I'm sorry to interrupt, but it's going to get late early.
Yep.
So, what I'm saying is, if I am a member of the public and I
say to my neighbor, "Hey, this unique growth zone really means high growth
because I've read it that way,"
is that true?
This statement is true. The Bug Light area
or Forest City Cemetery, those are
pure conservation zones. And there are
zones like Sable Oaks, like Maine Mall, which are
asking for unique and high growth.
But not all unique growth areas are also
seeking high maximum amounts of growth.
So that would fit somewhere in the range of what these two bookends are trying to
describe in this summary, that we have something at the extreme conservation end
and something at the unique high growth end, but we also have everything in
between, and you need to look at the CALUPA policies for what's actually
being asked for in each area.
Okay. I get you now, but I needed you to do all of
those words to explain to me what it means.
So I-
It actually confused me more. If we go to 64 of the actual plan,
there's nothing listed as unique high growth.
It's just unique growth. And so I was just-
Correct.
Is
unique growth high growth-
No
... on that page? Okay.
Unique growth is reserved for areas that are going
to change from what we know them to be today.
And if what it is today is an undeveloped area, and it
will be asked to become even low
density and pure residential, that's a significant change.
From an open space to a residential, that's big change.
It will still be called unique growth,
but it's rural. Our subdivisions out on Outer
Hyland in 2012 were called growth areas, maximum
growth areas, and they're single-family detached
homes on half acre lots because it took Greenfield
into development. Added roads, sewer, all the public infrastructure
that we built out there, right? The point of
unique growth is to say we are not trying to conserve what's
already there. We're trying to evolve it.
And so for the Eastern Waterfront, it is unique because it's going from a
industrial brownfield site that is
currently mostly gravel and dilapidated industrial
buildings, and the plan asks for a mix of
uses, residential in character, which has not ever been there before,
apart from the worker housing, and significant open space dedication was never
used for that. That's why it's unique.
It's different from what it was. The mall is unique
because it's adding residential and going mixed use, where for 60 years, we
said, "This will be a transaction business area, and that's it.
Get everything else out of there. We need to protect it for that." And we are now
taking a whole new paradigm, and on top of that, we want it to
be at scale. We want it to be big. So that's unique high
growth at the mall.
But what's been a challenge in the 2012 plan is we
asked for certain areas to grow, and when we
had community conversations about allowing that growth,
it never happened, and the implementation didn't happen because what we failed
to do in the planning timeframe of writing the plan is to say,
"What kind of change are we actually comfortable with?" People said
growth, but then they later had conversations about it and said, "Well, no, no, no.
Not that kind of growth. We want more of this other thing." And so we
had policy without real guidance and without asking the real questions of do
we expect change, something different
today versus 10 years from now if this plan is implemented.
And so we needed that fourth designation, which is different from the growth
designation because it's also a transformation.
Doesn't always mean the scale is being exploded.
Okay. I guess very different from
what's been there. Growth would've involved a lot of hyphens and been a
bit unwieldy.
But that basically describes it, and sometimes people will think
of what happens there as high, because it will be, and
sometimes not so much.
Okay.
One other thing that I just wanted some clarification on before we get to public
comments. Again, page eight, executive summary.
The plan also encourages the reuse of underutilized
industrial lands, particularly former
petroleum-related sites for new opportunities.
So my question, do we now in South Portland have
anything that we can legitimately call a former
petroleum-related sites, or are all of
the sites fully licensed,
and
are all of the tanks licensed to be filled?
We definitely have former petroleum sites,
but not at scale. For not whole farms that
are vacant, obviously.
I know of one former petroleum tank that is now
a boat storage, indoor boat storage inside the tank.
So yes, some sites have been converted.
We're working with a business that wants to be doing
offshoreconstruction and engineering
supplies. So they take out the cranes to build things like wind turbines and
whatnot. And so it'd be an offshore
service company that's operating in the footprint of a former tank.
Mm.
So yes, we have some sites.
It's not like the entire inland tank farm, for instance.
And then there are a whole whack of sites,
probably approaching 100 to 200 acres, that are owned by
petroleum companies that may have underground pipe there,
that aren't being utilized by tanks per se, but they're
not developed, they're being held,
and
could transition to something different than what that current operator might
have as their business.
Mm-hmm.
But they don't have a former above-ground tank that was sitting there.
All right. I would like to get to public comment.
So just one quick clarification left over from that is
what people think of the tanks, what they can see right
now, are those all licensed so that, for
example, I don't know what's going to happen and I don't think anybody else does
with oil and gas internationally.
Are they licensed so that if someone said it's a matter of national security
to fill all of them, that they could be?
I'd maybe defer to Scott, but to my knowledge, all the licensed
operators continue to maintain their licenses, whether they're
filling-
So that's yes?
Well, maintaining your license is different than keeping the tanks full at all
times. And so
my understanding is the tanks are all licensed.
They can operate at full capacity.
They are not necessarily all operating at full capacity all the time.
Right. So you've answered my question. You said they can operate at full capacity.
All right. I just wanted to get some clarification on that.
You hear very different things. All right.
Well, if no councilors have any other questions, I think the moment we've all
been waiting for is public comment.
Folks, if you could do a nice little line, that would get it done,
and we'd really appreciate it.
There's
a presentation going on.
Jessica, you got to switch this.
Okay.
Switch this.
Hang on.
If I could ask the gentleman in the back to switch our projection to show the time
for us.
Thank you.
That's wise.
Go.
Remember, name and the street you live on would be appreciated.
You don't necessarily have to give your whole address.
Here we go.
Leslie Ham.
Thank you.
All right. My name is Linda Zemsch, and I live on 225
High Street.
What is in the best interest of South
Portland residents?
SOS, Save Our Shipyard, believes that our
history provides the answer.
In 1941 and 1942, as
World War II was raging in Europe, two shipyards
were being constructed, the East Yard near Spring
Point Lighthouse,
and the West Yard, where the Sunoco tanks are now located.
The East and West Yards of South Portland together built
244 Liberty ships and
30 ocean ships. They were cargo ships
that were used to break blockades.
They came together quickly and then went overseas to
Europe transporting ammunition, artillery,
tanks, and sometimes even troops.
In order to do this, many people had to make sacrifices.
120 homes of working families were taken through eminent domain.
Many men went off fighting in the war, so women became part of the
workforce building these Liberty ships.
You may have heard of Wendy the Welder.
Workers came from all over Maine and New Hampshire to work here.
Between 25,000 and 30,000 people worked at the shipyards.
South Portland grew so quickly that it received emergency
funds from the federal government to provide for a dramatic
increase in population.
Meanwhile, down the road from the West Yard, where the old ferry
terminal was located, construction of the
Portland Pipeline took place. The original
12-inch Portland Montreal Pipeline headed down Sawyer
Street and then north to Montreal, where refineries were
producing gasoline and aviation fuel for the Allied
Forces.
The new overland pipe
solved the problem of the St. Lawrence River icing over,
which closed off winter deliveries, and it saved lives
and ships that had been victims of U-boat attacks.
Today, a park named after the lighthouse,
Bug Light Park, allows residents and visitors to view
the-
30 seconds
... to view the lighthouse up close while memorializing the
shipbuilding efforts of World War II.
And so the
history does indeed give us the answer.
SOS believes the development adjacent to Bug Light would take
away from the public that
which belongs to them and make the park a front yard for the
few who can afford to live there.We'd like to see a
larger park with a living shoreline, an example of
nature-based climate solutions
and
parks and-
Linda, you have to finish
... creating a park and a memorial is a one-time only opportunity.
Thank you.
Hello, my name is Rachel Berger. I live at 17 Churchill.
Can't hear you. We can't hear you. Rachel, you're going to have to try to-
Okay. My name is Rachel Berger, and I-
Keep that microphone. Pull it close to you if it helps.
Get it closer to my face?
If it... Yes.
Like that?
Mm-hmm. Very close.
There's a pen too, so you can actually bend it towards you.
How about that?
Ah.
There you go.
That's better?
Thank you.
Okay, terrific.
I have very personal reasons for supporting a shipyard
memorial. The Liberty Ships have a special place in my
memory as my family and I were at sea
along with those ships during World War II.
There is no doubt in my mind that America's Liberty Ships were
critical to winning the war by delivering essential
supplies overseas.
I was two when the war started. My parents had joined an
international Christian pacifist commune that included
Germans, so we had to leave England.
The only country that would take us was Paraguay.
My family, along with 80 other people, crossed the Atlantic
to settle in South America. But two years later,
at the height of the war, we and other Brits in our
group were called back to England.
My dad worked very hard to secure a safe passage for
us.
All he could find was a small merchant ship that supplied
Argentine meat to England. Hitler's wartime goal
was to surround England and starve the Brits.
We boarded our ships and waited for a convoy to travel with us.
Once we got underway, it was
slow going because our ship's bow had been
blown off
and replaced with concrete.
The crew was very worried about having children aboard
and made us sleep in life jackets with flashlights.
They told our parents to throw us out as far as they could
if the ships went down,
so the captain's motorized lifeboat could collect
us children.
As we neared England, the war intensified, and we joined a
21-ship convoy that included Liberty Ships
from the US. While adults
gathered in our ship's lounge to hear Churchill, my brother
and I slipped out on the deck to see why the guns were
firing. We saw a German plane drop a bomb a
few hundred yards from where we were,
from our ship.
Since England was surrounded by U-boats, our
convoy had to change direction-
Back end
... to avoid the English Channel. We were guided
around to another way.
In this way, the Liberty Ships helped the British Isles and my family
survive the war.
I think a memorial park on our waterfront would be a wonderful
tribute.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Susan Henderson on 9 East Street.
What Rachel said
about the Liberty Ships and
what Linda said about the Portland pipeline,
to me, these efforts
exemplify the best of our
nation, the skill,
the intelligence, the organization,
the use of resources to achieve a goal,
and it was a difficult goal. And that goal they
achieved. We won
and defeated Hitler's forces, and we
saved England and children like Rachel.
That was the task of the 1940s.
Now we are in 2026,
and a park
at the Eastern Waterfront
could exemplify
the best of what our country can do now.
Now our task is to keep our planet
habitable
and to keep it beautiful with open space that
people can use, and children can see natural
space and run freely.
This Eastern Waterfront
could be considered perhaps one of the most beautiful natural
shorelines on the whole Eastern Seaboard.
It's an amazing amount of open space if you walk
there a lot.
It is
a place that once developed will never come back.
When you're down there, you have this feeling of spaciousness
and wind and vistas and light on water
and clouds and peace
and little animals.
Somebody said once that the Packard property is nothing property.
It should be made nice. Well, the Packard property has been open
space almost for 30 years. And birds and little
animals and plants have grown there.
So
I think if we
couldDevelop that space
as an open space. It would be an
amazing achievement of this-
30 seconds
... city. And it would be almost a national achievement,
be akin to Central Park in New York or Prospect
Park in Brooklyn,
or
the Fort Williams.
So ask you to please
think of that space and its beauty. Thank you.
Barbara Dee, Scammon Street.
Good evening, counselors and community members.
I want to acknowledge the thousands of hours of this
little city has spent on the comprehensive plan.
The comprehensive plan committee, the planning department, and I will give a
shout-out to Eli,
the city council staff, community members,
Protect South Portland, No Yard South, Save Our Shipyard, petitions,
emails, letters to the editor, comments, surveys, meetings.
This has been an amazing show of devotion to South Portland, and we all
want the best for our community. The SOS committee, Save Our
Shipyard, asks the council to adopt option
three, which states, "Continue for substantial amendments,"
because we are requesting the creation of CALUPA 27.
CALUPA 27 removes 21 and modifies 22 to
allow the creation of the Eastern Waterfront Coastal Protection and
Heritage Area. K27 solves the community's
concerns with extensive residential and lodging development next
to Bug Light by providing a publicly accessible living
shoreline, a working waterfront, and a Liberty Ship
Heritage Common instead of housing or lodging on what we all
know is unsafe, contaminated land at the end of a
peninsula. On June 12th, 2025, the city
council held a workshop on the comprehensive plan.
At that workshop, I handed in a petition with 2,500 signatures
protesting any residential development in the shipyard zone.
I clearly remember the council in June of 2025
asking the planning department to scale back the density in the shipyard
zone and to change the growth designation from high growth to
limited growth. These changes were never implemented.
The agenda for the CPC on July 10th states, "Staff to
ask CPC to consider a new CALUPA number 27 as shown in
attachment." There was a map attached.
The CPC discussed and revised CALUPAs 11 to 27
to adopt the policies of CALUPA 27 as presented,
but modified the boundaries to roughly follow a line 300 feet from
the coast and separate the CALUPA into two areas, 21 and
22.
The minutes from July 30th reference the CALUPA formerly known as
CALUPA 27. So we are bringing it back.
We would like to bring it back. We want to revise it and revive it.
Because designating CALUPA 27 was a brilliant move
by the planning department-
30 seconds
... to address community unrest about development in the shipyard zone.
K27 has everything in it that South Portland needs.
Open space, working waterfront, nature-based coastal resilience,
brownfield remediation, nature-based infrastructure, continuous
public shoreline, a Liberty Ship memorial, an expanded museum, and a
plan for after the tanks are gone. We have everything to gain from
K27. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I'm Josh Cutler from Bay Road.
I once read that once upon a time in Maine, it used to be said that a
man who owns a boat owns an island.
Today, that's no longer true. Many islands are closed to visitors,
even those with a boat to get them there.
Most land on the coast of Maine is privately owned and inaccessible to
Maine people.
Businesses and people who rely on water access see it
diminishing. Some of our recreational and working waterfront, Bug
Light Park and the Eastern Waterfront area of South Portland, are threatened
by the language of the draft of the comprehensive plan.
As part of the process of exploring funding for the future Liberty
Shipyard Memorial Park so that burden doesn't fall to the
city,
I've described it to funding organizations, including the Maine Coast Heritage
Trust, the Trust for Public Land, and the Conservation Fund.
They understand that more people can enjoy nearby parks with ocean
access and views than can visit remote preserve sites,
often offshore, that still require the boat
and a lot of vacation time as well to get to.
I suspect that many more people visit Bug Light Park on a weekday afternoon
than visit some of the more remote preserved lands in an entire
season.
Does the proposed comprehensive plan advance this vision?
It is possibly true, as we've heard, that land use policy for the
Eastern Waterfront area articulated in the plan in
K21 and K22 does not preclude the
goals of the proposed K27, which we've put before
you this evening. However-
Could you speak slightly... Could you speak up slightly?
Yep, sorry.
Thank you.
However, acceptance of the plan in its current form adds to the
complexity of achieving these goals by assigning further discussion
of them to planning and zoning processes to follow
later.
These processes would have a better roadmap,
in Milan's terms, better guidance, if the
preservation goals for the district are clearly described in the
comprehensive plan. They've already been advocated for and
endorsed by literally thousands of South Portland citizens
through comments before the CPC, through written
petition, and through electronic comments on the
plan.There is an opportunity to reconsider the land
use policy for the shipyard area. I urge the council
to vote option three in the planning director's letter and take time-
Seconds
... to consider and adopt the policy goals expressed
in Save Our Shipyards CALUPA 27, so that the
final accepted version of the comp plan
expresses a clear vision of an accessible, open,
eastern waterfront, and marine protection and heritage
area for the people of South Portland and beyond.
Thank you.
Can you hear me?
No.
Hi, I'm Linda Skinner, 824 Sawyer Street in South Portland, where I've
lived for 35 years now.
We all know that South Portland is in desperate need of housing, especially
affordable housing, and we need housing that serves a varied
population and a range of incomes, from young families and single
professionals to essential workers and students to retirees.
South Portland is already the second most densely populated city in the
state, and as more people are drawn to our town, that population just
keeps growing, accelerating the need for residential development.
The comprehensive plan clearly aims to meet that need.
20 of the 26 CALUPAs in the plan are flagged for residential
growth of varying degrees. That's a lot of new housing to put in an
already heavily populated city.
That additional growth will take several forms.
There'll be ADUs on existing properties and smaller lots
and multi-story buildings for new residential.
The trade-off for more housing is much smaller yards per dwelling.
People who live in densely populated neighborhoods need open
air and green space for their mental, physical, and social wellbeing,
a space like the proposed Shipyard Memorial Park on our eastern waterfront,
and that could be easily accomplished by adding 27, page 27, back
into the plan.
Right now, we have Bug Light, a local treasure that sits on the edge
of a tract of open space marked for three to six-story
buildings, including residential.
A lot of people think that's a bad idea for obvious environmental and safety
reasons, but it's also the last undeveloped stretch of waterfront in
southern Maine, and locals and tourists alike are drawn there daily by the
beauty and peace. We have a once in a lifetime opportunity
here to expand and preserve this lovely waterfront park for the public to
enjoy until the sea ultimately claims it.
In the meantime, it would be protected by nature-based infrastructure, the
most cost-effective and durable response to rising seas.
South Portland is known and respected as a green, eco-friendly city.
We owe it to present and future residents to create housing in a way that upholds
that reputation. Thank you.
Thank you very much. And I forgot to say thank you to Mr. Kepler.
Thank you, Mr. Kepler.
And could you hang on for just one second, John?
Yes.
I'm unfamiliar with chairing hybrid meetings.
Do we do all of the public comments in the room and
then check on whether there's someone?
I do. I don't have any hands up right now-
Don't have... Okay
... but that's a good reminder for folks online.
If you do have comments you wish to make, please hit the raise your hand button.
Okay, thank you. And then also, I think Milan, you might be in control
of this screen. Oh, whoever's there is-
That's up.
Oh, that's you. There was a request to show what council's
options are tonight.
So that's Milan's slide. Do you want me to put back his Milan slide?
It is Milan's slide.
They have it on the screen. They have to...
Okay.
But will we still be able to show the timer, though?
Nope, so this screen will remain on for the time for public comment.
Okay.
And then once we've concluded public comment, we can switch the screen back to
Milan's to show the options.
Okay. All right. Hear that, everybody? Can't show the options quite yet.
All right, John Pawnee, I believe.
Well, I don't have to say it.
Thank you.
You just did.
Thank you, counselors. John Pawnee, Beach Street.
I have to both speak to the microphone and see what I've written here.
Sorry, we're full of tricks.
Lean in to VR.
John, I'm going to come down and read that for you if you want me going.
If you would.
The eastern waterfront is a derelict and
currently useless property.
It could, however, provide great value to the
city.
The difference between what it is worth to the city now
and the value it could bring in tax revenue and public
benefit, that difference is striking.
Appropriate development there would help to solve a serious
fiscal problem.
The city is unable to fund basic needs at this
time, and without a change in course, the
situation is going to get worse.
The eastern waterfront is privately owned.
The city cannot just take it,
including it is illegal by state and federal
law
for the city to make that property worthless by aggressive
zoning. You cannot do that.
The city or some nonprofit would have to buy the property at
current market value. That's the law.
I do not see that money materializing.
I don't see where it comes from. The city needs to
work with the people who own the property.
We should negotiate with the owners who live locally,
they live nearby,
to provide a development that includes public benefits.
Development could include small business,
eating establishments, and housing, and would
benefit the publicIt would be
perfect for including amenities
such as open access through the
shoreline area,
walking trails,
bike paths, and connections between the Greenway,
Bug Light, and the SMCC and Willard Beach
areas. All we have to do is
negotiate.
There are challenges to developing there.
30 seconds.
We all know them,
but they can be mitigated.
They can be solved. We can solve those problems.
The shoreland zoning is a beautiful example of
solving a problem. That was brilliant work and it's an
example of mitigation.
The Comprehensive Plan Committee has spent years putting
together an excellent plan that is thoughtful,
careful, and responsible.
Time.
It provides guidance that points the way to reasonable
opportunities. We should adopt it and move forward.
Thank you very much.
My name is Brian Nickerson. I live on Pine Street in Ferry Village, but I don't
want to talk about Ferry Village. I'm talking about the
Kalupa that's right under our feet right now.
I've been working with Tim Honey, the coordinator of the Toss the Tanks
initiative, and specifically the redevelopment of the Hill
Street tank farm right next door, currently owned by
Suncor Oil out of Canada.
Tim, by the way, he's in New Zealand, and he wanted me to give you
his regards. Both he and Deborah are there for
about a month on both islands.
The Toss the Tanks initiative wants to thank the Comprehensive Plan
Citizens Committee for their hard work and the long hours they've had to put
in in the past two years to create an excellent
2040 comprehensive plan. We want to thank the committee
for including specific language in the plan regarding the Hill Street
tank farm that sets forth a vision and strategies for
removing all 19 mostly empty tanks.
By doing so, it'll set the stage for the property to be
transformed into a mixed-use development,
primarily focusing on housing needs of the city.
This is the first comprehensive plan calling for the elimination of this large and
underutilized tank farm. Redevelopment of the property should
address two of the city's most important priorities, housing and
expanding city tax base.
This redevelopment could generate an estimated at least eight times
or $4 million, the amount of annual property taxes now
being paid for by Suncor Portland Pipeline
Incorporated.
We urge the council to
unanimously
support the 2040 comprehensive plan for the city, and we urge the
council to support the Hill Street redevelopment plan, which calls for the
elimination of the 19 oil tanks at the Hill Street facility,
replacing them with a more compatible
mixed-use redevelopment of housing, community
services, offices, retail, and open space. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Kay Michigan, Romano Road.
Thank you, councilors, for this opportunity to make a statement.
You have worked long and hard, as well as the committee,
to determine how South Portland can navigate into the future.
Thank you so much for that.
Foreseeing the future is difficult and it weighs heavy in
responsibility,
and this document that we're looking at
is really heavy lifting. I'm sure you all want
it to be done.
Among all the difficult and complicated issues of today,
this for you could be one box ticked off,
done.
But it's a changing world and things are
uncertain.
I would ask you tonight to please take a deep breath
and pause
before this final vote.
This is too important to make a decision you might
regret.
I've been attending some meetings of the Comp Plan Committee and hearing
various presentations and discussions, and
I have been convinced that there are some clauses
containing
that need to be changed that pertain to the Eastern Waterfront.
I think residential development in this area is not
wise.
I know South Portland wants to strengthen its
finances by getting more revenue from real
estate taxes. That's good.
South Portland needs more housing. Yes, we do.
Residential building is allowed in many of the city's areas
and could address both of those issues.
But the narrow peninsula of Bug Light is not a
place to allow this development, and we've heard all those
reasons over and over.
And now we have a suggestion to create a park in this area.
This would protect the city from the impact of
development,
and in turn, probably generate additional
revenue
as a destination site
for residents and those from away.
I believe the average South Portland today is in the dark
about all the things we're talking aboutBecause we
lost our media print presence-
Seconds
... and community issues such as this comp plan are not known
to most citizens in spite of what we've heard tonight.
The hardworking families and young people in South Portland no longer
have headlines facing them on the countertop or in the newsstand.
And therefore, a lot of people have been left out of this process.
They'll be shocked when they hear the results.
And yet, these are the folks who have the most to lose
and the most to gain from your decision. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Come on up.
Elaine Salekis, Strathmore Road.
Thank you, council members, for this opportunity to speak and for your hard
work.
I'm deeply connected to Bug Light and my community, and I
urge you to please pause and
review.
Not to go right into this comprehensive plan and
start changing zonings,
growth designations, and future development frameworks for the Eastern
Waterfront.
I oppose shrinking or curbing this remaining beautiful, accessible,
and historic space. Caving in to the developer to
change zoning would give them carte blanche for
anything they want and set bad precedent.
No matter all of the language that is used and all of the word
salads that are going around for the comprehensive plan, there's a
lot of language in there, even with unique growth and
high growth, that can be parsed. We live
in troubled times of division, war,
anxiety, high costs, and even finding
out and questioning what is real. We need
community, and we need nature, and we're losing both
quickly.
South Portland has much to offer if we stay true and
open to the treasures we have that are worth preserving,
not exploiting. It's all well and good to see little round dots,
and circles, and flat sections of land,
supposedly illustrations, but we don't see the
impact of that on our lives and what would
actually happen.
The treasure that no dollar can measure is Bug Light
Park and surrounding land, providing a respite from the
24/7 news cycle. A place to engage with nature
unencumbered, and to reduce stress, and
enjoy and engage with our neighbors in simple
pleasures
with walking, picnicking, kite flying, and exploring our history.
To me, this proposal is an elitist community
destroyer that will, if passed, irreparably change the identity of South
Portland. We can try other options,
such as the SOS proposal.
I lived in Long Island, Maine, and the council couldn't
wait. They rubbed their hands together once they separated from
Portland and thought, "We're going to make a lot of money on selling
these lots."
30 seconds.
And then they hit oil because of tanks that were there buried.
And people that put money down on them from out of state,
they demanded their money back. The bottom line is that think about
the Eastern Prom in Portland, Maine,
a treasured community oceanside green space.
If they had approved a plan like we are going to try to
approve now, it wouldn't even exist.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Good evening, Mayor, council members.
My name is Thomas O'Boyle. I serve as the advocacy director for the Portland
Regional Chamber, representing 150 businesses in South Portland.
Can't hear you.
Thank you.
Yeah, my name is Thomas O'Boyle. I serve as the advocacy director for the Portland
Regional Chamber, representing 150 businesses across South Portland.
We appreciate the significant work that has gone into the comprehensive plan by the
committee, staff, and residents.
It's also important to be clear about what this plan is and what it is not.
It is not a site-specific development approval.
It is
a policy framework that sets direction
while preserving the council's discretion as individual projects come
forward. From the chamber's perspective, the most important outcome
is that the plan supports housing growth, mixed-use development, and economic
activity in appropriate areas along corridors in Sable Oaks,
Mill Creek, and parts of the Eastern Waterfront.
These are places where thoughtful growth can occur while still respecting
surrounding neighborhoods. On the Eastern Waterfront specifically,
the plan does not enable unchecked development.
It establishes a conditional framework.
Any residential development would require further environmental review, including
emissions and health impacts. This ensures decisions are
guided by science and regulatory expertise while allowing the city to
plan for productive application of underutilized land.
That growth is essential to the city's fiscal health.
South Portland is facing rising costs, difficult choices around school staffing
and facilities, and significant long-term capital needs.
Without expanding the tax base through new housing and commercial development,
those costs are not avoided, they are shifted onto existing residents.
More broadly, the plan establishes South Portland's growth path for the next
15 years. The choice before you will shape whether the city remains
accessible and economically resilient for the next generation.
This plan strikes a reasonable balance.
It supports diverse housing, grows the tax base,
and addresses environmental and infrastructure concerns responsibly.
For those reasons, we encourage the council to adopt the comprehensive plan and
move forward with implementation. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Do I get to use the rest of that time, too? Oh, no. Too bad. Okay. Hi.
Claire Holman from Ferry Village.
And I just want to start out by saying,
I strongly believe that South Portland needs to remain
a small city. Small cities are the nicest places to
live, and I have it from the authority of none other
than Councilor West, that in fact, all those
places with great density, they don't have lower property taxes.
One of our biggest burdens is the property tax.
And sorry,
I thanked you so much for giving me that information.
And,
so what we're looking at is we are depending on property tax, a
regressive way to get money, and that it's forcing
development on us. It's forcing us to use open spaces as a piggy bank for the
future,
and I don't think we should be. I want to ask, please, will the city
leaders, the city council, insist that we direct
the people who can do it, whether it's the city planners, which are economists, to
really push harder for some other ways for us to get money besides
property tax. It's going to sink us.
It's going to force us to have things that we don't want, and already we're a
densely populated area.
And I definitely support the bringing back K Looper 27 and
this SOS plan.
Because just take a moment. Imagine Fort Williams.
Imagine if a few hotels over there,
a few houses, a couple six stories in the background.
It would never be anything like what it is, and we're talking an even smaller area.
It sounds like it's going to be kind of okay because there's going to be green
space. I wonder how much green is going to be left.
At least there's something, and I know that so much work went into this, but I
really question the wisdom. Also,
will the city council please assure that if we're going to
have corridors, because corridors means that buildings are going to be lining all
those streets. Okay? That's like a city.
Many cities have buildings lining all the main streets.
We need trees. This is New England. Tree-lined streets.
Not those little things that if you bump into it with your car, one plow hit,
it's over. Okay? We need actual trees.
Yes, there's some work, and they actually give us something that you can't get
back. So I want to know, will the city council ensure that we're going to have
actual trees along these so-called corridors?
Just go over, I'll spend a lot of time in Red Bank these days.
Those two new Avesta buildings, they have these little, one plow hit
things in the front of them. They're not nice buildings.
They're the typical, "Here, poor people live in this." Sorry.
I'm sure they're probably perfectly adequate, 100% adequate, but they're not
beautiful, okay? But if they had at least real trees in front of them, it wouldn't
matter.
So, thank you very much for that, and I just want to say
that
we
just really need to drive forward in a way that doesn't force us always to sell
ourselves out so we can get more property taxes.
It's really a shame what we might end up doing to ourselves, because
it doesn't end. There's no end to it. Just goes on forever.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
My name is Marianne Hill. I'm an economist and a resident of
South Portland, and I've been very impressed by the discussion tonight.
I think that both the city council and all the residents of the city would
welcome a wonderful expanded park at Bug Light
Park if there were private donations that funded
it. So I've been looking at the financial feasibility
of such a park.
And I believe that it is possible and reasonable to
expect that adequate funding could be found from private donors,
especially if there were the moral support of the city
behind it.
An expanded park, in fact, of course, would bring vast
economic benefit to the city, raises the city's ranking
in livability, which is important in attracting
businesses and high-skilled employees who
value cultural attractions and green
spaces.
And of course, I agree with the last speaker, there is a great need for tax
reform so that cities have more options for raising funds.
But I want to point out an important alternative that the city of Portland is
now piloting, a tax on nonprofits.
We have 288 nonprofits here who
have
hundreds of millions of dollars in property with income of
over half a billion per year. A small property tax
on these nonprofits would make a huge difference to the city, bring in
much more revenue than what you would get by development right around the
Bug Light Park area.
And let's look at what's some numbers regarding the current city
budget. The city budget last year was 151
million, more or less.
Development near the park might bring in three or four million.
However, along with that additional revenue, you'd have
additional expenses.
Once you take out those additional expenses,
you would get about $2.5 million, which is
less than 2% of the city's budget.
Excuse me. And in addition, you have the problem of sea
level rise remediation, which costs $100 million,
actually a bit more than that, over 50 years, which is about 2 million per
year. So with that in mind, you hardly make any-
30 seconds
... funds.
And of course, the park itself could generate a lot of
revenue. You could have an expanded museum that would
bring visitors.
You could
host weddings and various fairs. Look at the 100,000 people that
come to the Yarmouth Clam Festival.
There are lots of options for fundraising with a wonderful park.
And the legacy of our city would be expanded.
Time.
It would tell the history and it would
Bring
the city together as we celebrate the history of shipbuilding and our
work during World War II.
Thank you very much.
Hi.
My name is Liz Torocca. I live on Reynolds Street.
And I have a question, and I'll ask for forgiveness if
the answer to this question is somewhere in the plan that I haven't read.
So sorry about that.
My question is about affordable housing
and how the plan, or if the plan,
presents a citywide
approach to affordable housing in
terms of
suggesting or prescribing percentages of housing
that should be considered affordable, how
affordability is
calculated and whether that
is a comprehensive plan domain or it's
something that the city council
would set policy around a goal for that in our
city. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Hello, everyone. My name is Angie Helton.
I have lived on Bergen Street for more than 20 years.
I have a PR consulting firm that I've had for a couple of decades, and I currently
am the president of the South Portland-Cape Elizabeth Chamber of Commerce board of
directors.
First, thank you all, to the council for your service and to the planning board
members and staff for the time, effort, and dedication you've brought to developing
a comprehensive plan for our city.
This has been an extensive process involving thoughtful discussion and
careful consideration by a group of residents who want the best
possible future for South Portland.
For that reason, I'm here to support moving this plan forward and to encourage its
adoption tonight.
It's important to note that adopting the plan does not lock in every detail.
Many components will still come before you through future ordinances.
This plan provides guidance. It doesn't override existing rules or
require you to adopt every recommendation.
As we all know, South Portland needs to strengthen its tax base.
The city's financial challenges are not on hold, and delaying the
implementation of a plan that establishes a solid framework for housing
and economic development only makes those challenges harder to address.
For these reasons,
I, as a longtime resident, a local business owner, and a chamber member,
respectfully ask you to approve the plan as presented this evening.
Thank you again for your time and your good work.
I was going for shortest testimony. I think I won.
You may have. Thank you so much.
I favor it.
You're about to start. Let me just check in on the online situation.
What were you saying?
We do have a hand raise online from Debbie Davis.
Okay.
Debbie-
If you want her to go first, that's fine
... would you-- Okay, let's let this person know that we are
taking online
comment.
So Debbie Davis, if you could unmute yourself and go ahead.
You have three minutes.
Is she there?
How's that?
Yep. Good.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
Okay. Thank you.
Thanks for all the hard work, every city council.
Hello?
We can still hear you.
Comprehensive plan.
The whole
community, thousands of hours, everybody.
Thanks for that.
I want to echo Claire's value of a small
city
as a bottom line.
I also want to
give kudos
to Mariette Hill. She's a very experienced economist,
and she's done a lot of assessment around the financial feasibility
of SOS's plan. And I would also like to put a vote in for
SOS's
plan and supporting
their plan for Memorial Park. It could be a legacy,
a historical
place, very powerful. If anyone's been to UNESCO sites
around the world, these are really amazing
places.
This is an incredible gem. We have
access to coastal green space,
which benefits us all immensely in so many ways.
It's priceless. It increases our mental and physical health and
well-being of residents, which is right in the mission
statement in the beginning.
I've talked to a lot of young people around us,
and they don't need to live right on the coast, they just need
access. A big green space,
just like
various areas, Eastern Prom,
Fort Williams. These places are amazing, and they do
generate income. And it invigorates the whole town,
including economically.
And it does not make sense,
financially or otherwise,
to develop in areas with toxic
soil,
near tanks, tank hazards,
at the end of a peninsula with traffic issues
and congestion already, in areas
prone to compound flooding and sea level rise,
and-Problems with an aging infrastructure around sewer and
groundwater. Come on, folks. Let's think of
looking all over the city. I love the idea of
having these small, little centers,
downtowns. I think that the planning committee has had some
really creative ideas around that.
We just have to know where it makes sense to do all of these things.
And I like Clea Holman's idea too, of expanding,
instead of just property taxes, expanding other revenues through
businesses, et cetera, like that.
The business people speaking have a lot of passion. We have a lot of energy.
Time.
We need them in our town too. Thank you very much,
all of you.
Thank you very much.
Okay, and thank you for your allowing that.
Go.
It's your turn.
My turn. Hi, my name's Dave Burkey,
225 High Street. I'm part of SOS. I'm here to
ask the councilors to choose option three and to
adopt CALEA LUPA 27. The first thing I'd like to do
is to thank Misha Pride, Carter Scott, D**k
Andrews, and Jessica Walker over the last week for
meeting with me and us
on holidays, when on vacation, out of country.
I have been very impressed with the council and how
responsive they are to me, a citizen, and so thank you for
that. I'm very impressed.
I would like you to imagine two scenarios.
I want you to stand at Bug Light on the
plateau in the year 2036.
You are looking on a beautiful day like today out at Casco
Bay, and you're looking at Diamond Island.
You then pivot around to your left, and you look at Portland Harbor,
and you look at the eastern prom. You look at the Maine
State Pier, and then you pivot around, and you look west towards
Fore River. Scenario one, you see
condos,
hotels, and residences
lined up along Bug Light Park.
How will that make you feel?
These residences will not be low income.
They have 720 degrees of water views from
Portland to Casco Bay in the islands.
These are going to be $2 to $4 million each.
There's Radisson Hotels there. It's going to be 1,000 bucks a night.
We're not looking at affordable housing here.
We're looking at very high-end, wealthy housing.
Scenario two, you turn around and you look at Fore River, and
there's a park there. And in the middle of the park, there's a
memorial to the efforts of folks at South Portland
during World War II, victory at sea. Think about it.
We should acknowledge that. It's not in the plan. It should be.
The way to do that is with CALEA LUPA 27.
The way to do that is to accept our history
and listen to the folks as they come up to the mic, 10 to
one, 20 to one, in favor of this.
The last thing I'd like to say
is that regardless of the vote tonight-
30 seconds
... regardless of the vote tonight,
I have met with Dave Packard, and I'm actually optimistic
that we can work with Dave and his sister, Jennifer, and come up
with green space idea. But I would love to have the
city of South Portland, the councilors, back that.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Good evening. My name is David Field. I'm at 64 Summit Street.
I've basically thrown out everything that I had prepared to say,
but what I do want to say is that I get it,
is I get the fact that PK Realty owns this property,
is that so many, we've got all these great plans.
Let's build the shipyard. Let's do all of this.
But I want to go back to the very beginning and what
we are supposed to be. We're supposed to be a representative
government.
And, in the early days when PK first
purchased this property, it was purchased as industrial.
And you go back to the very beginning in their websites and the
notes, it talks about how they were excited to
have additional commercial space, and that was
the business that they were in. And so, that
was the direction that they said, and the properties
fit into their business.
Then you go forward a couple of years, and all of a
sudden, we start having these huge development
types of programs going on. And then you go take a look at
some of the minutes of the meetings, and they talk about
how, "Gee, we really like the plans that
you're coming up with and the vision that you're putting
forth for the city."And so then you keep going
forward, and then all of a sudden you've got Yard
South. And I think the people started saying, "Wait a
second. Take a look at the hazards, the flooding, and
all of that." But everything had been marching
towards doing this big development.
But the public, we talk about being representative, and I'd be
curious too, as to how much of
public input is saying, "We want these big buildings.
We want this." Supposedly, I thought our
government is supposed to, if we have got
a strong feeling. Now, the good news is here is
that if they had focused on, okay, let's take a
look at what kind of flood-tolerant, low density,
and those types of structures could be built out there
within a modified, with that zoning that they
bought it in. You could be really creative because
there's so much need-
30 seconds... for you take a look on a summer day, all the boats out there, there's so many.
There could be some marine industry.
But you build it low density, you don't have the impact
that all of this development that it's had.
The other issue I think is we're sort of ignoring is the flood issue,
is what the base flood elevation is.
You have down in Boston, all the areas flooded out there.
So anyway, that's what I have to say. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
The line got longer behind me.
Good evening. Reverend Allison Buttrick Patton.
I am the senior pastor at First Congregational Church, United Church of
Christ,
the church on Meeting House Hill. And
I
want to add my voices to those who've expressed real
appreciation for the energy, the time, the creativity that has
been invested in this process over
the last
many months,
and just share for a moment about a tiny part
that we have played and therefore, a window we have into this
process. About a year ago, First Congregational Church had the
privilege of hosting a community forum in
collaboration with the citizens' effort that's called Toss the Tanks, that's been
lifted up once this evening already.
At that forum, we gathered close to 100 South Portland participants
and asked what might be possible if the Hill Street tank farm was
removed and the 100 acres of property somehow
redeveloped.
SMRT Architects of Portland created a theoretical
design for the space to help us imagine the
possibilities.
And at the round table discussions after that presentation, there was
so much positive energy, and I think an
appreciation to be invited into imagining
all of the different ways that we can build community
together.
I want to acknowledge
the values that you lifted up
at the very beginning of this presentation.
In particular, the commitment to climate resilience and to social
vitality, because those are values that we embrace and talk about all the time
at First Congregational Church. It's really exciting to see
those elevated as part of this
discussion. We heard interest in those
values mentioned in the room that night.
We also heard housing.
It emerged as one of the top priorities as we talked together, which is no
surprise. You all have heard that as well.
If anyone's curious, the whole SMRT presentation is
still online at tossthetanks.com,
and you can take a look.
What I just wanted to lift up is how exciting it is to see a
comprehensive plan that includes the potential to transform
the Hill Street tank farm into a mixed-use neighborhood with a focus
on housing.
30 seconds.
And
it's so clear that the work we have to do to implement is
considerable, but the vision is worth pursuing,
and we look forward to partnering in whatever way we can as we hold onto
those values that you have lifted up from the outset.
Thank you so much.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
Good evening. Kathy Chapman, Beaufort Street, and thank you,
counselors and Mayor, and of course, the CPC that did lots
of
years and hours of hard work on this
proposal
draft comprehensive plan.
But I do think, and while I think that most of the plan I agree with,
that's probably 90%, maybe 99%, I do think that it
needs some revision in the shipyard zone.
The public,
as you know, as you've heard tonight, and as when we had Yard South,
Barbara D. presented for us
the petition with 2,500 signatures.
And everyone tonight, I would say, would agree
that that petition said no residential in the shipyard with the
Chalupa, which was, I guess, 27. I guess it's now 22
under the new updated version.
The other two pieces to that were a low
density, low growth, which was reflected in the survey that was done
actually by the planning, although they
seem to
analyze it differently. But that 60% of the people said they wanted low growth
in that area.... and being flood-tolerant
uses
because that area, as many speakers have said, and as we know through
science and climate change in your very own South Portland flood
maps, that there will be flooding in that area.
The CPC chose to use 3'9",
but you can
give the statistics on that on how when I
was at that meeting,
given that 3'9"
scenario, is considerable flooding, and I think it was
more than once every two weeks. That's a lot
of
water. I'm thinking a foot, but I can be corrected by Milan, I'm sure, that can
give the actual statistics on that flooding.
But that was considered okay by the committee.
I personally don't think that's okay for housing
in that area.
And I would prefer
to see, as we had already seen before,
the marine uses be predominant and
recreational marine-related uses
that could include restaurants, marinas, fishermen, lobstermen, piers,
recreation, that they used in the past, and is part of our Maine
tradition. I'm a native Mainer, and so I really feel strongly that we
should continue that heritage that was in South Portland and in
Maine as a whole. It's kind of our brand in Maine.
I'm also concerned with bug light.
So not having the residential is a key thing, not having high
growth. We are the highest density city in the state,
or second to Portland, depending on who you ask.
Time.
So we certainly have a lot of density. I'm not against housing.
In fact, I'm pro-housing. That's why I'm against residential in this area, because
we don't want housing that will be flooded-
Your time has ended
... a 50% chance in 50 years. So we can't do that,
so please do the right thing for our future. Thank you.
Next doctor.
Priscilla Scary, a naturopathic doctors of South Portland.
The human exposure model must be adopted by the tank farm owners.
In your review of the 2040 comprehensive plan, it's in a current form.
Please understand the problem of designating most of the shipyard district as
unique high growth. This is the opposite of the
expressed desire of South Portland residents, especially those living close
to the tank hazards and the possibility of floods.
As a South Portland naturopathic doctor, I've talked to you before about the need
to acquire tank farms near residents to adhere to the VOC
human exposure model, known as the HEM model, and
establish appropriate buffers. Why?
Well, you are about to make public policy that will affect people's exposure to
cancer-causing compounds.
In a letter
I sent to Portland Press last year, I expressed a need to insist on proper buffers
between industry and home, and mentioned why, given the work that the
community had done over the previous decade to protect public health from the
unknown 40 additional tons of health-harming volatile organic
compounds, otherwise known as VOCs, such as benzene and
neurotoxins like ethylbenzene and xylene.
But back then, the citizens
achieved a victory via the Clear Skies Ordinance, stopping tar sands from coming
into South Portland. Then fence line monitoring was worked for after
three EPA lawsuits against the tank farm allowing
emissions violations. These weren't abstract concerns.
They're about preventing respiratory, neurological, and immune system impacts on
citizens. While no model is perfect, the HEM model was good
enough to support passage of state law.
In my opinion, it's clear that the HEM model is a very good
approximation of what the neighborhood is likely
increase in cancer and other disease rates would be.
The science hasn't changed. Benzene still causes cancer, and especially leukemia in
children. Ethylbenzene still damages the nervous system, and toluene still
harms childhood development. What our actions changed back
then was our willingness to ignore these facts.
Demand that new residential zones not be allowed near tank farms.
We must continue this. We must insist that tank farm
owners recognize the harm that comes from the toxic fumes in these tanks, and
yes, from other sources, too. But adding the HEM model and insisting
that the fossil fuel industry adhere to this, must be done if we,
as citizens, matter to this corporate world we are all a part of.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Georgia Deveras, Victory Avenue.
Good evening, Mayor and councilors.
Two minutes.
I've spent the last two-plus years alongside many of my neighbors,
attending meetings and following the comprehensive plan process.
I'm here tonight not to rehash the friction of the past, but to talk about
the city we love and how we move forward together.
For over 20 meetings in more than two years, many of us have shown up to comp plan
meetings, sent detailed emails, conducted and shared
in-depth research. We didn't do this to be difficult.
We did it because we care. But I want to be honest with you,
at times, it has been a heartbreaking process.
There was a profound sense of a void where the public's voice should have
been. When 80 residents show up to speak and are silenced, or when
state statutes have to be read from the podium, it indicates a wound in
our local democracy that we now have the chance to
healOn June 12th, 2025, the council
gave a clear directive to the planning department to reduce the growth level for
the entire shipyard. However, the 2040 plan only
applies that request to a small fraction of the area.
Instead, the rest of the shipyard is designated as D,
unique high growth, the highest growth level on page eight.
We are asking for a plan that respects the physical limits of the land
and protects the health and safety of the community.
It has been difficult to watch the disparity in how voices are heard.
As residents, we aren't looking for special treatment.
We are simply looking for a seat at the table.
Our research and our lived experience is an asset to this city,
and yet our attempted contributions were openly mocked and
disregarded by some committee members.
Meeting after meeting, the committee and planning witnessed this,
and nobody stood up for us.
Despite the challenges of the last three years, something
beautiful has reemerged. I want to point you toward CAELUPA
27, the Eastern Waterfront Marine Protection and Heritage Area.
This proposal isn't just a redrawn map, it is a labor of
love.
This vision for CAELUPA 27 is a product of collective
imagination, refined and clarified through research and
analysis, and a shared commitment to our community's future.
It addresses the dangerous tank emissions, the traffic, the brownfields,
flooding, and sea level rise, and aligns with the stated priorities of the
plan. It is a profoundly meaningful, and I believe beautiful
vision and solution for the shipyard area, and a legacy for this city
council.
Many of us feel a bit damaged by the toxicity of this plan's process,
but we are still here because we love our city.
Restore the public trust, adopt a plan that reflects the community it is
meant to support and protect. Let's embrace the vision laid out in CAELUPA
27. Please delay your vote and adopt the Eastern
Waterfront Marine Protection and Heritage Area into this plan.
Time.
Thank you for listening, and thank you for your careful consideration.
Thank you very much.
Hi, my name is Prudence Bean, and I live on Henley
Street. And I've lived here about 16 years.
Obviously, I'm here because I do support the idea of
leaving Bug Light as a park. It's very important.
I think about Counselor Walker talking about the
people who rent homes on the west side of the city.
This
area is an area to come to within South Portland to enjoy being
outside.
So, and I think this is a legacy that we want to leave for our children and
grandchildren, this open area, one of the last few open areas
truly on the coast of Maine that's accessible.
And I want to just tell you about two instances.
I used to
be the treasurer of the Maine Lobster Festival, and we had
one last piece of open oceanfront land in Rockland on
Main Street. And we bought that land and deeded it to the
city because we wanted to make sure that there was still open land for
everybody to use. And then I also want to point out,
Coastal Maine Botanical Gardens started as an
effort of families who said they didn't want to see development.
They wanted to put something in that was going to draw people to Boothbay,
and they mortgaged their homes to buy the original land that the
botanical gardens sit on. And that started a whole
venture of finding the money to keep this organization going.
It's possible for a community to come behind something like
this and make it happen. I've seen it happen, and I think we can
do this, and that would be a good purpose for this city. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Hi.
Mary Linneman, Simmons Road, South Portland.
I want to
add my voice to everyone who has commended both the
Comprehensive Plan Committee and the city councilors.
Your attention and your stamina has been tremendous.
This week, tonight, you have the opportunity to
slow down the implementation of the comprehensive
plan that the CPC has put
together.
Please allow the citizens of our city to be
truly represented in their desire to save the Eastern
Waterfront
from unwanted growth. We're asking you to
designate this area as CAELUPA 27 or
22 and 23, whatever it's called, with limited
development, allowing for commercial fishing and
aquaculture
uses, and prohibiting housing, lodging, and
hotels.
The shoreline should be designated as a resource
protection zone.
There are currently unanswered questions relating to flood rules,
cost analysis, impact fees, and environmental
monitoring of tank farm emissions.
These questions need to be answered before a framework is
adopted that locks in a plan that does not meet the needs
of our city in a changing and a more expensive
environment.
I would urge you again to take a look at the proposal to use this
land to develop a heritage site,
recognizing the achievement of hardworking ship builders
and the sacrifice of homes that were lost to build
the shipyard during World War II.
South Portland is unique that we have this little space in our city.
Bug Light and the Eastern Waterfront are our most beautiful
parcels in South Portland. They're our Fort Williams.
They're our Eastern Prom.This designation would
also allow for nature-based infrastructure along
the waterfront, which would be a cost-effective response to
sea level rise.
Please consider the requests of those of us in South Portland
who have asked you to save our shipyard, to delay
approving a plan that has unanswered questions,
and who are looking to save open space for the future.
I add my voice to those urging you to adopt option
three to promote the policy goals of Save Our
Shipyard. Thank you.
Hello, councilors.
Thank you.
Robert Foster.
I'm Mary's husband, and I live on Simmons Road as well.
I've been a South Portland resident since 1993.
Some folks who know me may know that before I moved
to Maine, I lived in Florida,
which may or may not seem relevant,
but I think it is. My experience there was that I
watched, to paraphrase Joni Mitchell's
famous song,
paradise get paved and put up a parking
lot.
And
one of the things that I have loved about living
in South Portland is, one of the many things I've prized about
living here, is the value this community places,
in my experience, on preserving its heritage and preserving
its green spaces, preserving its natural beauty.
And when I moved to Maine, I pledged that I would do everything I
could to prevent Maine and the
little part of it that I lived in from turning into South
Florida.
That may seem
supercilious, but I'm very passionate about that.
I've seen what happens when
development is allowed to dictate decisions that get
made in a public forum at the
expense of environmental beauty,
aesthetics,
and
just those things that are maybe
abstractions, but they're incredibly important.
Some comments have been made about the potential
value of this parcel as a tax and
revenue instrument. I certainly understand
that. On the other hand, I would submit that
value cannot be calculated simply in terms of dollars and
cents,
that these intangibles
that I just mentioned are of extreme importance to
the citizens and to the future citizens.
I would urge the council to consider option
three, to consider
revisiting CALUPA 27,
and to think about the people who will follow
us living here who will either thank us
or condemn us for not taking a
courageous stance and preserving what
is unique and beautiful about the community we live
in. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Good evening, PJ Cragun, and thanks all around.
I reiterate all the thanks that have been said in this room tonight.
Smith Street, and
speaking on behalf of Protect South Portland.
We have worked hard for an entire decade on
petroleum harm reduction. We've done
a ton of research.
In all of our research, we find the same exact information:
that tank fumes are dangerous to people's health
and can cause cancer.
This has just been something that we cannot avoid
find...
Sorry. Getting around to this health study idea is that somehow this health
study is going to determine something different, that is going to say, "Well,
maybe it is safe." There is nothing in the research
to indicate that the fumes coming out of tanks are safe.
It's just simply... So then you get down to exposure, then it's
how much is safe? Well,
during the Clear Skies Ordinance, there was a doctor that spoke on behalf of the
City of South Portland, actually, who said that
no amount of benzene is safe.
So I think that's really where we need to begin this
conversation, is how do we avoid
exposing people unnecessarily to tank fumes?
We spent $3 million to stop a tar sands terminal
because that was going to bring 40 tons of volatile organic compounds
into our neighborhoods. And now we're having very real discussions
about putting a neighborhood next to 50
tons of volatile organic compounds, and we're saying, "Well, if we
do a health study, then maybe it will say that
it's safe."
So how this health study would likely play out is the Maine Center for
Disease Control would probably be the seminal authority on whether or not it's
safe. Well, the Maine Center for Disease Control also did not
mention between 2013 and 2019 during the global
lawsuit that we were being exposed to what they were
investigating as dangerous amounts of, or
overshooting their emissions permits.
The Maine CDC did not alert the neighborhood after the Sprague
lawsuit... that they had been polluted over their emissions
permit. The Maine CDC did not let the people who lived around
Bug Light and the Gulf Terminal when they exceeded their benzene levels.
There's still people in the neighborhood who don't know that they were exposed to
benzene at illegal levels.
I only found out word of mouth, and-
Next
... this is kind of what we do. Okay, I'll stop there, but I think I've
spoken to enough of you about that.
And this issue of CALEPA 27, which I think is an excellent
idea, it does make a difference in your comprehensive plan.
How you have it now, it will be pretty well up zoned.
So with the CALEPAs 2021 and '22, those
are significant up zones which make their job
significantly more difficult. So I do think that it's a
big difference, CALEPA 27 and what it lays out and what the plan
lays out. Thanks so much.
Thank you very much.
Hi, good evening. I'm Paul Cunningham.
I live on Edward Street.
And first, I do want to commend the Comprehensive
Plan Committee for working
so hard for so long. I can't imagine the
amount of work that's gone into it.
I attended a handful of the Comprehensive Plan
Committee meetings, and I too am very concerned
about
the tanks, about the
vulnerability to flooding with
sea level rise, and I'm also very concerned about the
traffic
on Broadway and how it will affect the surrounding
communities. I don't think
from a traffic
standpoint
that
our community can handle
the type of development that may transpire in the
Eastern Waterfront.
So
I wanted to talk a little bit about
the CPC meetings themselves.
As I said, I attended a handful of them, not a whole lot of them,
but
I came away from them
sort of perplexed and
I found that the reaction to public comment during the
meetings was really
strange.
It wasn't adversarial, but
I was left with a sense of sort of non-acknowledgement.
Not by everyone on the
planning committee, but
there was a general
reaction, though, as though people
who had just spoken didn't exist, or what they had just said
hadn't been spoken. People expressed their concerns
about
the tanks, and potential ocean
rise, and the traffic, and then
the discussion just went on to
how are we going to develop the Eastern Waterfront
as though no one had spoken. And I don't really feel like we were
listened to. I guess that's my general consensus.
Second.
And
hopefully, city council will listen to us. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Come on. And if there's anyone else who'd like to make public comment.
My name is John Howard. I live on
Dimar Drive in South Portland.
Not too long ago, I was talking to a
commercial airline pilot. He had just
landed the plane that I had been a passenger
on. My seat was towards the rear of the plane,
so by the time I got up to the exit, the cabin
crew was getting ready to leave the plane.
And so this pilot and I walked out together into
the terminal. I asked him a couple of more or
less technical questions about landings, which
he was only too happy to respond to.
He reminded me of an eight-year-old kid who
became fascinated with aviation.
But anyway, when we were done, it was not a long
conversation. I asked him if he had a
favorite airport to fly into, and
he said, "Portland, Maine." He didn't hesitate
for one moment. He said, "Portland, Maine."
And as all of us know, the majority of the Portland
Airport is located in South Portland.
And he said that
coming up on a clear day, a water
approach, flying over the coastline from
Saco and Scarborough into Cape Elizabeth in
South Portland,
every time he did it, he was amazed at the
green open space, and the
sense that gave him of peace and
relaxation.
I didn't say this to him, but I hoped that he was not too
relaxed landing a commercial airliner.
But
as other speakers have said tonight,
this is a gem. It is known
wide and far. AndAs
someone else said, once it's gone, it's
never coming back.
And this pilot's almost his closing words to me,
parting words were, "I hope it never changes."
So I hope all of you will keep that in the
forefront-
30 seconds
...
as you decide what to do here. Save our
shipyard. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I have to say, public comment doesn't usually make me tear up, but
I fly fairly frequently, and that's how I feel coming
home.
All right. Do we have any other comment?
I already speak.
Pardon me, did you already speak?
I did.
Yes. Well, we appreciated your remarks, but you cannot speak
again on the same topic. Thank you.
Is there anyone online?
Last chance. Anyone online to raise your hand for public comment?
Do not see any hands raised.
Okay. All right. Well then, on this item, the public
hearing for our recommended comprehensive plan is
closed.
I know that we have some decisions to make and some discussion to have, but
would anyone on council mind if we did-
There's a few questions.
Oh, well. How about this? Does
anyone besides the mayor need a five-minute break?
How about Scott answers the questions, and then I would really love to have a
five-minute break. Five minutes.
Even better, Milan answers the questions.
Okay.
He's been taking-
Thanks
... copious notes again. I think there are only a handful.
I did not
capture too many questions.
There were two for the council. Will you insist on
pushing for other ways to get money instead of property taxes?
And secondly, from the same speaker, will council assure the
corridors maintain trees?
At least on the trees piece, that's a pretty straightforward
zoning standard, and we can certainly include that at the council's discretion if
we do look at zoning along the corridors.
The next question that is more directed to planning staff was a
question about affordable housing, how the plan provides
for affordable housing citywide. Is there an approach?
What's the calculation method? What's the definition?
So the plan includes a... It's broken down into two
parts. Part one is the one that has all the policies.
Part two is the inventories and appendices, and that goes
into length on matters of housing policy and our
conditions in housing, and defers to the housing assessment
that we did to define some of those conditions.
And both of those sections really give
some background on how we would define affordability.
In this community, we would define affordability as below
housing that serves households earning less
than 80% of the area median income.
For for-sale units, it can go up to 120% area median
income. Those definitions are pretty
standard across how the state looks at that, how the
federal Department of Housing and Urban Development looks at
defining affordable housing. We, in the plan, also
recognize and use this term of workforce housing, and that reaches
households that are between that 80% of area
median and 120% of area median. And that's a
tough group because there are no federal programs or state
programs to help support housing that serves them, and they're also a
group that isn't necessarily able to access all of the market
rate housing, and so they're squeezed from both ends.
They're not poor enough, but they're also not rich enough, and so
really hard to find housing. We speak to that specifically in the plan.
We have citywide policy.
Specifically, I'd call your attention to Goal 3A,
and then also 7H that speak to affordable housing.
There's a variety of measures. We talk about anti-gentrification,
anti-displacement, looking at inclusionary housing policies, allowing for
infill housing, allowing for small-scale housing that
can be squeezed into existing structures that typically come
in as more affordable support for the ADU program, which
has been statistically shown to be affordable housing.
And then as well as other forms of deed restricted housing, so
using affordable housing TIFs. All of that is specified in the plan.
So we kind of approach it from any and all possible ways that we can
participate in promoting, and we have a generalized policy of just do
anything we can to support affordable housing development, and
specifically restricted affordable housing.
So happy to dive further if needed on that.And
I think that's all the questions I had.
Yeah.
One thing that I would add on it too is, I'm not
sure what the CDC did or didn't know back in
2019 about those lawsuits. I'm not entirely sure they knew
anything. So it's possible they did.
It's possible they didn't. I would presume, and we can try
to find this out by asking them, if they did know and felt there was a health risk
or concern, that they would've alerted South Portland and the residents.
But that's not what happened, and we found out like many people through
a newspaper article unfortunately, at that
time. And I also don't think it's necessarily a new study
or report that would necessarily be used to help us understand the
risks. It would be some part of the ongoing monitoring efforts that
frankly are set to wrap up in one phase this
June when DEP and CDC come in to give us a combined
report. Those reports so far have said the risk right
now is, as has been stated before,
out of the entire population of South Portland over a 70-year period,
if the exposure at that kind of worst area was
constant, you would expect one
additional cancer in the entire population.
And so it's possible with new and updated information that that could
change. That doesn't talk about short-term acute impacts, but that's what
the information has told us so far.
But again, we're going to get more information from CDC and DEP this
June. And then there's the whole fence line monitoring, which are
showing,
as probably anticipated, elevated levels at the fence line, and so we need to
figure out how is that dispersing into some of the neighborhoods.
Some of the neighborhoods are almost essentially living on the fence line, and so
how quickly does that disperse, or is it all just going into the neighborhood?
So I think with what we've got going on now, we're going to have pretty good
understanding.
There can be more that's done, but I think we've already got a pretty good
understanding of what's out there, and then that can be used as the
basis
when the council considers whether or not those areas are safe for residential
development.
Councilor West, were you asking a question, or...?
I just thought it would be useful for staff to clarify one thing that we heard
just in almost the last testimony, the assertion that the housing
would flood every two weeks with the level of
sea level rise considered in the plan.
And I have maps if we need to look.
We have done sea level rise projections at 3.9 and 8.8
plus, and with and without storm conditions.
I haven't seen data that specifically says every two
weeks there will be flooding. The mapping we have shows
average daily high tide condition, as well as a high tide,
like a king tide annual condition, and then that 1% storm.
We do also have depth information associated with that.
But if you fast-forward in time long enough,
with what we know about sea level rise, there will be a point where water
becomes very frequent. However, the current projections
that we're looking at are at the 2050 mark and then
over to the 2120 mark. And I'm not
sure that widespread throughout the shipyard we have any areas that are on a
biweekly basis experiencing water. I'd have to take a closer look.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Could we just please have a five-minute break?
It's 10:25, and just come right back here at
10:30 and decide what we're going to do next.
Folks. All
folks, if we could
quiet down a little. Thank you.
And our thanks to Officer Gerrish who figured out how to turn the lights
on in the hallway.
Yay.
Okay. So it is 10:31, for anyone
who wants to know. And we were going to begin
council discussion by giving an opportunity
to the two council members who served on the comprehensive planning
committee a chance to make the
first comments, and then we're , excuse me, I think we're going to
talk some more and figure out what we're going to do here.
Is there a motion for passage that we're going to have?
Or are you part of the presentation?
Pardon me?
Are you part of the presentation, or is there a motion for
passage that needs to be on the floor?
I don't know. This is a little odd because we don't usually say to-
Oh, it should've gone before public comment, but it's okay.
Okay. We don't usually say that. And now the committee
member councils will simply have some things to say. So you're right.
It's just a process question.
Generally, when we're speaking, we have a motion...
I mean, we could probably do it either way if it really bothers you.
The original plan was to give us a chance.
Go ahead.
Or just make the motion so it's done.
Or you can make the motion.
I'm not motioning anything.
Okay.
I'm not motioning anything at this moment.
Holy cow.
Councilor West?
I make a motion to adopt as presented with a clear revision
I'm going to suggest.
And I'll second
.
Very-
For purpose of discussion
... your motion.
All right. Well, now you can make your comments.
No, because you're the mayor, you can go first.
Oh, okay.
Didn't you want to go first?
No, I was going to be polite and let you go first.
Okay.
But whatever works. I can go first. I'm ready.
Do you want me to go first now, Marie?
Sure. Go first.
Okay. So basically, all I really wanted to
do was, the
most important thing to me was to sayThat I
really acknowledge and feel grateful to
everyone who has come to committee meetings, who has come to
this meeting, who has come to other council meetings, who has
brought comment and has brought research, and
others who have written to the council and written to the committee
members. I
want you to know that we read our email, that
I heard you, I hear you now, I
acknowledge all of that, and I'm grateful for it, and I'm grateful to live in a
community where this happens.
So that was my most important thing.
Yes, I served on the committee, and in doing so, I didn't just sort of
read or hear from others. I saw the thing unfold in real
time, and I heard concerns and disagreements,
deeply held perspectives from residents, from business owners,
others who care about the community.
And now here we are at a different stage.
It's the council's responsibility to review the committee's
plan and decide whether it's ready to be adopted or whether
changes are needed before it is.
And
based on what I observed during my time on the committee, what I have
heard here tonight, I do believe that there's still work
for the council to do, and I don't support
immediately moving forward with the plan as is.
I think we've heard that there are consequential elements.
Mostly those relate to the Eastern Waterfront.
And
I feel that in some cases at the committee
level, decisions, as our chair alluded to,
decisions were made by relatively narrow votes.
And
the conditions were such that although we have a
16-seat committee,
two of us didn't vote, and not all seats
were actually filled at all times.
So although quorum numbers were met, it still
meant that on some significant decisions, a fairly few
members voted. And it just makes
me a bit uncomfortable because I think what we ended up with is a
plan that reflects a divided set of views rather
than something that was widely supported.
I'll mention my experience of the original K Lupa
27.
It did come to us after staff had taken a great deal of
time and trouble and brain power to meet with
every member of the committee who wished to and had come up
with this idea of a K Lupa
27 that, as I recall, many of
the committee members liked, and also it met
with some good positive comments by community
members who had previously not felt very good about
where they thought the direction was going for the Eastern
Shipyard area. So it was surprising to me.
Actually, I got on a plane thinking that, "Oh, this K Lupa 27,
it's saving us. Thank you, staff." And then I got off the plane and
found out that it hadn't passed. And again, it was
a fairly small number that legally
could vote and be a majority, but it was a small number of
16 seats. So that does bother me. Now we're
here at our council level, and I do think that our
council has shown in the past that we can take a closer
look at things, and that we can be influenced by what
members of the public, our community, our neighbors have to say.
I thought of, well, there was gas-powered leaf blowers, and some of us
thought that was a great idea to have a moratorium on them.
And then we heard a lot from the community, and it was not a well-supported
idea, and we pulled it back. And then I see what the school
board's going through now. They're listening to parents who are
asking them to slow down on some ideas.
So I am not saying we need to start over.
I'm not dismissing at all good work that's done.
But I think there are some places where we could still discuss and
make adjustments, and I do think that that is our
council role for something of this
magnitude.
My view is that we should adopt tonight with a revision that I'm going to
suggest. It was suggested by David Hebert.
I want to start off by thanking everyone who's here tonight
and thanking the members of the public who have participated throughout the long
process. I've been serving on the committee since I was elected about three
and a half years ago, and it makes me
sad when I hear people stand up and say that they weren't listened to because we
did. We did listen to you, and we incorporated
many of your suggestions. We revised and
considered. And the committee was made up of a
cross-section of our community, as it should be.
But to hear people stand up tonight and say that we took
into account the property tax effect of
development in the Eastern Waterfront is not accurate.
It is true to say that there was a group, there were several members of the
committee, who believed that we should have intense development in the Eastern
Waterfront as a way of generating property taxes.
But their view was the minority view. It did not prevail.
The prevailing view for the Eastern Waterfront, and most of my comments are
going to be about the Eastern Waterfront, because as you can tell, that's what
people are talking about. The prevailing view is that
some sort of balanced development is
appropriate.We've heard talk tonight about the
petition but the petition that was submitted
said, "As a resident of South Portland, I added my name
to this petition to express my opposition to any zoning
change in the city's shipyard district that would allow
intensive high-rise residential development
like that proposed for Yard South."
It did not say, "I oppose residential
development." And I've spoken to many, many of you in the
community who have told me that you recognize the need for
residential development. Balanced, low-density
residential development in the eastern waterfront could
be appropriate.
I want to say that I do think also as we go forward,
regardless of what happens tonight, we need to have another
workshop about implementation because three points that are very
important to me are, I think the council has
to have an annual review of our comprehensive plan.
We need to have a public proceeding
in front of all of you where we, who are elected to represent you,
look at what the plan has done, what we've accomplished in the last year,
and how we can proceed and set priorities for its
implementation.
I also think the city needs to take the initiative to engage with
Portland Pipeline and Sunoco to determine their business
plans and do what we can to end hydrocarbon storage
on our eastern waterfront. We've heard some testimony tonight that
nothing should happen because of the toxics, but I think the
better approach is that the toxics should come to an end, and
then something can happen.
With regard to the park,
I support a park.
I actually think that a park would be better if you can focus
on K Lupa 21 instead of K Lupa 22.
K Lupa 21 extends along the Fore River.
It is the waterfront area. If you look at the parcels...
Well, I could go on for quite a long time.
As you know, I get into the details, and I know it's really late,
so I don't want to lose you. Let me just say that I think that I support
a park,
and I would suggest that
if the group of people who want to have the park wanted to work
with the city, that the city could form some kind of a committee,
and work with the citizens to see if we can have a historic park.
I've talked to a number of you about this.
I also think it's important to ask our historic society to be a
part of that. And I understand there's dynamics, but we know they have a lot of
expertise and a lot of knowledge, and if we're going to have a historic park, our
historic society should be part of what goes on.
I thought the speaker who referenced the Maine Botanical Garden as a
reference, that was a pretty useful idea to think of that creative and
what that has done for that area. And I think a historical park could do the
same for South Portland.
With regard to the discussion on growth, the state statute
says you have to decide if it's rural or growth.
So we have
kind of tweaked it a little bit to say limited growth and unique
growth. But the statute says when you identify your land, you've got
to say whether it's growth or not growth.
So that's why our staff has done such a good job.
And I do want to say, I hope when you listened to our staff presentation tonight,
you realized how absolutely outstanding the quality of our
staff has been. That was a clear and detailed,
and I hope
you could just have a lot of your questions answered by
what a good presentation that was.
In particular, how long it's going to take between now,
which is trying to get our basic framework in place so that we
can do the things that we need to do.
We have a coastal resilience overlay zone that's close to being
ready to go. We need our comp plan in place
to bring that forward. We probably need to have some development
impact fees. We need our comp plan in place so that we
can start working on development impact fees.
I
guess I won't go into all the
other questions, but I do want to say that I thought David...
Oh, I've got to talk a little bit about the toxics.
Yeah, we should be concerned because benzene is dangerous, and the latest
fence line monitoring from the Sunoco site shows
that 14 of those measurements exceeded our
state level.
One of them was seven times our state level.
That is not acceptable, it's not safe, and I don't
support people living close to it.
But again, the answer is, let's get rid of the tanks.
And so in our plan, we have a lot of
protection. We have these necessities to make findings
before anything could go forward with residential in that area.
But when Dave Hubert stood up tonight, he suggested that we
insert one sentence, and it would go in two places after the
word occupancy to say the evaluation must
incorporate the maximum potential
to emit. And I would
submit that we would add that to the plan
and that that would be appropriate with one of
the actions that we're entitled to
take tonight, which would be the clear revision that I would suggest as
part of our adoption. So that's where I'm coming from this evening,
and I appreciate you giving me the time to speak to these points.
Thank you very much, Councilor West.
Just-
A point of our process, and we want to move to the other
councilors' comments.
If the other councilors also have specific
changes to suggest, this councilor might have a couple,
how are we going to basically handle that one?
Because often we are making amendments to one
thing that is a short thing. These are
not short things.
Can I just offer a suggestion?
Yes, please.
I think that each councilor should offer their amendment via a motion, each
separate amendment, and then have the whole council vote on each separate
amendment.
All right.
Unless your amendments depend on each other, and then you can put them together.
But if they're independent-
All right
... it's going to be a process, but it's the way we should do it.
Councilor West, do you feel that you've offered that to your own
satisfaction in amendment language?
No. I'd make a motion,
maybe someone will second,
that in
5C14,
after the word "occupancy," we add, "The
evaluation must incorporate
maximum potential
emissions."
I second that.
And then also in CALUPA 22-
B.
B. Is it B?
Yeah. It's-
Yeah, B, after the word "occupancy," insert the same
phrase
or sentence.
I second that as well.
Okay.
So do you want to have a vote on... Anyone have comments
about the amendment?
I'll just say that I support it. I had 5C14
as an area that I wanted to discuss as well, and I think that sentence that he
offered really gets at-
Yeah
... our concerns.
Okay.
And everyone's in agreement that we're sort of offering amendments-
Mm-hmm
... at this time.
All right. Well, do we do a roll call vote on this amendment?
Seems like we do. And there's Carter hanging in there.
Thank you, Carter.
All right.
Can we have the roll call vote?
Yes, ma'am.
Thank you.
Councilor Scott.
Oh, can you-
You're on mute. She's mute.
Did we have to put the volume back on the TV from earlier?
Oh, yeah. There we go.
Oh, hang on, Carter, sorry. Technical issue.
It's Scott's fault.
I'm getting a little punchy.
Yeah.
It's frozen now.
She was talking.
There. Now she's-
She's-
There we go.
All right, try it now.
Oh, almost.
Getting there.
All right.
Yeah.
There we go.
Okay. I approve of the motion on the floor to
amend the comprehensive plan as Natalie suggests.
Thank you. Well stated.
Councilor Walker?
Yes.
Councilor Coleman?
Councilor Pride?
Yes.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Yes, ma'am.
And Mayor Tipton?
Yes. All right. The emotion ca- The emotion.
The motion carries.
Thank you.
We're open for business on other motions that actually would
become amendments to the motion on the floor to pass the
plan.
Councilor Walker.
I'd like to
amend the comp plan to
include timelines on all of the places that don't currently
have them. For example, goal C. Most of goal C doesn't have a timeline.
There's also several others that don't have timelines.
I would leave it up to the staff to determine what is the appropriate timelines,
but I'd like to see timelines, the short, medium, long, filled in there so
that
we can measure against those
goals.
Okay. So as an
amendment, I think it's amended to
direct staff. Can
you help with these things?
Can you repeat your rephrasing?
Yes.
I'm saying that it sounds as if she wants an amendment to
direct staff to complete timelines.
Right, which might fall into a different category than a discrete
amendment-
Yes
... that could be passed right now.
Unless you want to phrase it, Councilor-
Can you say that again, sorry
... more specifically. I think if you phrased it as specifically, maybe as
Councilor West did, then it could be an amendment that could be passed by the
council. But I think if it's a directive to staff, then it might fall into a
different category.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Okay.
So I'm just going to talk about it, and then you can tell me if there's a way to
amend it.
City manager to direct staff to do that.
Just I noticed there were several goals that did not have a short, medium, or long
timeframe attached to them, and I would-
Yeah
Shouldn't we be directing-
I think we're just going to fill them in
... All right. Shouldn't we be just directing the city manager to
direct his staff to do that, and not us?
I'm just asking, just for clarification.
Yeah, I think if we can just get specific about which
sections will be amended-
Okay
... in what way, then the direction maybe could be to the city manager.
Well.
Well, we'd probably skip it if there was five missing, and you say they should all
be medium term, then it's done right now.
Right.
Yeah. I think that's the thing, is that just there's data missing, and I would like
to see the data point filled in.
Can I suggest that we come back to that amendment, maybe at the end?
Okay.
It'll buy me some time. It may be that it was just a PDF export
problem, and I want to verify if we actually have the data points.
If we don't, I might be able to come up with the suggestions now,
and then if you agree to those, we can run with those.
Okay.
Okay. Thank you.
All right. Others looking for amendments, or
Counselor Walker, did you have a second one?
Come back to me.
Okay.
Yes.
All right. Well, are there others suggested at
the moment?
Counselor Scott. I would like to jump in.
Counselor Scott, hello.
I did try to raise my hand. Is the audio okay? I know there was an echo.
The audio's good now, yes.
Okay. I can also lower my hand. Okay.
I do not have any specific
motions or amendments to
move, but I did want to speak to the plan and just provide some
commentary, and obviously you folks can move on from there.
There have been some thunderstorms in my power slam, so would love to
get this
on.
Wow.
That was the world's worst timing.
Ironic. You couldn't plan that any better.
Oh, my God. That's heartbreaking.
At least she explained what was-
That's heartbreaking
... gonna happen.
Oh, poor Heather.
Wow.
Can she come back?
If she can come back.
Come back, Heather.
That was a-
Come back.
Oh, but she's frozen.
Nope, she's back.
Nope, her mouth is moving. You're back.
You were-
Is it now working?
You're back. You cut out for about 30 seconds.
Temporarily gone. So please-
Classic
... speak if you would.
We have profound things to say now.
Okay.
Sorry about the back and forth. I do not have any
motions or amendments to make on the comprehensive plan.
I wanted to provide a few brief comments, and please let
me know if this glitches out. I first wanted to
speak to the way that we are speaking to each other, and I have been disheartened
to hear in many different scenarios and discussions in
South Portland that we have, I think, felt
disrespected or dismissed. And I have seen this on all sides
of the discussion. So, this is not to any one group
or one side of any of these arguments, but I hope that we can speak to each other
with respect and
again, all sides going forward, and make sure that we are open to
communication and hearing everyone's arguments.
So just wanted to put that out there.
I think with regard to the comprehensive plan, thank you so much for all of the
work that has gone into this, all of the public commentary, and the hours
and hours that have been spent on this plan.
I am in support of moving the plan as is forward, and am happy to hear
and
decide on motions as we get there.
I want everyone to know that air quality and toxic
fumes are incredibly important to me, and I do believe that
we have a lot of work to do as a city to continue in this effort.
I just don't believe that the level of specificity that has been
requested is appropriate for a comprehensive plan.
I believe very strongly that we need to be planning for and
appreciative of climate change, and I think that the climate resiliency
overlay zone is an incredibly progressive and forward-looking
step to move in that direction. I know that there is
great concern about soil contamination, and I believe strongly that
we do have the technology... Oops, let me make sure I'm
not... Nope.
Did you lose me again?
We're still here.
Keep going, good.
We're here.
Okay, great.
I believe that we have the ability to remediate that, and if we give up on
areas of our world that have been
challenged by environmental concerns in the past, then we really have given
up on too much.
There were many comments and many requests for different areas of the plan
to be amended, and many of them, I think, are just far too
specific and not appropriate for a comprehensive plan.
Thousand-foot buffers,
specific modeling requests, there's many out there.
I just don't think that that is appropriate for a comprehensive
plan.
Regarding the Save Our Shipyard and expanding the Bug Light Park,
obviously, this is near and dear to all of us.
I don't think there was anyone that would not be in
favor of expanding Bug Light Park, both to the south with the
PPL properties and elsewhere across the city.
So I want those members to know that I am
in favor of this. I'd love to sit down with more of you and
talk about this and see about ways that the city can partner with your
organization, with other organizations, with private landowners, to
expand Bug Light Park and to make part of this vision happen.
I think it is very inappropriate to do that through a comprehensive plan and
zoning, and I think
I can go on and on about this, and I'm happy to have more conversations, but I just
don't believe that that's the correct way or the legal way to
go about this. So happy to continue to have that conversation.
I've started some of those conversations, but please know that my support is there
for Bug Light. I think the last thing that I would say
is in thinking about whether or not we send this plan
back, I've heard lots of commentary, both at the
comprehensive planning meetings, in emails, in discussions with people.
If I were to send this plan back to the comprehensive plan or put a
motion forward, it would actually be to remove the lines and remove the
specificity in the Eastern Waterfront and allow for the
zoning process and the specifics to play out.
Lost it.
All right, just a little bit. It would be to remove...
I don't believe the specificity, the
lines, the heights,
the commentary in the Eastern Waterfront is
appropriate. I appreciate that it was done and I'm willing to accept it, but
that would be
the amendment that I would request.
So that's sort of my compromise, just going forward knowing that.
I believe this area is severely down zoned, and I'm very
concerned that we keep pushing in that direction, that we're going down
a bad path.Again, happy to discuss all of
this. I think the last thing that I will say, and this is not
necessarily part of the comprehensive plan, but hearing the
discussion and the arguments, I hear so many
comments that say, "I want to live here, and I don't want
anyone else, any more people to live here." And that is
a statement that says, "I belong here, and you don't."
And I can't tell you how
sad and disappointed and angry that makes me feel,
because when I moved to this town, I wanted to belong, and I wanted to be
welcomed. And I hope that new residents who come, people who
want to move into South Portland, feel welcomed, and that we are able
to create and enable a space for them to be and for them
to belong. So, I appreciate all of the arguments
about air quality, climate change,
all of those. I don't appreciate the arguments about we don't want any more
people in our town. So, I would just encourage people, as you think
about everything that you do in this space, what is your
privilege to be here? How
are you presenting yourself? How do you welcome others?
Are you being inclusive, or are you not being
inclusive? And I think if we take some of that away, and we sort
of spend a little time processing and unpacking some of those
emotions, I hope that we can come forward with South Portland and
welcome new people and build the housing that we need, and
build back our school populations and really have the
wonderful community that I think we all love and hold dear.
So, that's my last comment. I'm supportive of this plan.
I hope we can move it forward. And I'm really excited to get into the details
of the actual implementation and getting some of this policy work
done. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Carter. You came in loud and clear at last, and
we're happy to have heard your comment. Thank you.
All right.
Yes?
I just figured while people are considering more amendments, I can filibuster a
little more because I have none to offer.
But I would like to address the comprehensive plan.
And
I, like Carter, would move it forward as written.
I want to support her
in that
all of you probably didn't see all the emails we did .
And there were many people who emailed us saying things that had the
air of,
"We live here. We don't want anybody else to live here," and that kind of stuff.
There were people who emailed us who said that, and that tone was not appreciated.
And so I can understand where she's coming from.
She was speaking to the wider audience, not necessarily the people in the room.
So I just wanted to clarify, at least I don't want to ascribe her motives, but I
believe that to be true, because I don't feel like we heard that much from you all
tonight. You all had similar concerns to ones I've always had as a councilor.
I am for open space. I supported the piggery being purchased by the--
I supported the open space bond. I supported this new property that we
have by Pilgrim Road, and having that remain
conservation space. I've been repeatedly
someone who's very
much in favor of environmentalism in the city, sustainability.
I started getting involved in city politics when they were suggesting that we have
propane unloading in the railroad yard, and I was really
against that, and it was one of the things that influenced me to
get involved and eventually run for council.
And I supported the continuation of the lawsuit
against the Clear Skies Ordinance that we eventually won
while I was mayor of the city. I was proud of what we did as a
community.
As part of that, I testified to the legislature supporting fence line
monitoring, and I think that support helped get us that law
in place, and I'm proud of that.
I was a key vote in getting the tree ordinance passed.
I'm the one who tried to get the
leaf blower ordinance passed and had my life threatened for it, which is a
little crazy still to say that out loud, but it happened, and we ended up
sort of dropping that. And part of me still feels we need to get rid of
two-stroke engines in general because they are just horrible emissions
producers and horrible for the person operating it.
But that's not what we're talking about tonight.
Tonight, we're talking about the comprehensive plan.
And if we look where we were in 2012 when we passed the
comprehensive plan, we will see why city staff
talked to the Packards and talked to them about developing that land the way
they did. Because it specifically says in that comprehensive plan
that city staff, city basic policy is to
encourage good quality development in this area.
To accomplish this objective, the city should actively work with property
owners. And it doesn't specify no residential.
Now,
they asked for a zone change, and in fact, our planning board
said, "Yeah, that fits with the comprehensive plan because staff is supposed to
work with them," and it doesn't say anything about it not being
residential. And what ended up happening, I think, and I
can't say this
with complete clarity because they withdrew their application, but I think
they spoke to some councilors, and including myself, because I know they
did, because I spoke to them. And I made my opinion public, which was
that I don't think the people who bought near the
shipyard, who bought near that zone of what it's
zoned as now, working waterfront, thought that there would be a
development. And the people who bought near it get to rely on that
zoning.
That's just my opinion.
Now we're talking about a comprehensive plan that doesn't
necessarily say there's going to be
residential. It says they have to meet certain requirements that we get to set.
That was one of the purposes of my question early on to Milan
about who gets to decide how
the health of the
people living nearby the tanks is assessed. We do.
We could set a really, really high bar.
If you guys continue to support councilors who are
environmentally minded, we can set a really high bar for
developers to meet before we allow residential, and they may never be able to meet
it because we can set the bar that high. It's allowed.
So
I think it's interesting because I
live right up the hill here. So every morning, I pull out of my
driveway, and I see the Hill Street tank farm, every morning.
And if you look at another Nutter Hill neighborhood, the K
Lupa 16, which has been applauded by people, including Toss the
Tanks folks, who obviously have an environmental bent to
them, but if you look at that K Lupa, it
says, "Amends zoning to primarily encourage the development of complete
neighborhood, mixed residential, and light commercial." So in this
area, we are promoting light residential,
and
that's right near the tanks. And I just don't hear folks saying, "Well, how can we
allow light residential near the tanks?"
They're not all in use, and I
haven't seen the fence line data there.
In fact, I think maybe one or two of them are in use.
But if they suddenly all were put into action,
I think I'd be in trouble, and I live uphill,
potentially. Maybe the downhill is good for me, but it's not good for Kaylor
School while it's still
open, I guess.
But all that being said, you look at that
K Lupa 16 language is very much okay with
residential. If you compare that to the language in
22 about residential, where it says residential should only be
permitted if they meet this burden of having a health assessment.
That's very different language. And again, it's policy
guidance, right? We have the 2012 comp plan says the city
should work with a developer to get as
much suitable development that matches the neighborhood, which would include
residential, as possible. And yet, that didn't happen because the
zoning is what I think defined it in most councilors' minds
what should go there. And I think that's why the Packards
withdrew, because they talked to me and some other councilors who all said, "Well,
it's not really zoned for you. You should've thought about the zoning when you
bought it."
It's the zoning that's really going to offer that granularity,
and that's why I support the plan as is because I think it supports zoning
that is restrictive, that will make it so housing is difficult to go
there because
we, the decision-makers, are people, I think, who will support that
higher standard in zoning. That being said,
I went
to Josh Cutler's house, and I saw the presentation on the park, and that does
excite me. I would totally support that. We don't own the land.
That's my one thing. And we, and the school, we're all
in a big fiscal,
kind of looking at a fiscal cliff here.
And so us buying the land is almost an impossibility.
I know that the Packards bought it, what, 7.7 million in 2018.
Even without
us talking about it, the land has gone up in value.
And people tell me that if the city says they're interested in a parcel, it
doubles in value,
just automatically. If the city's going for it because the people who own land
think the city's pockets are as deep as they need to be because of bonding and
whatnot. So I
am totally for it. Just like Carter, I would support it
wholeheartedly. I'm happy to continue that conversation and see what
things we can do to make that a reality.
I just agree that I don't really think it fits in a comp plan.
I think zoning, but zoning's only going to happen if someone else owns that
property because we can't zone someone out of their
property. That just would be illegal.
So that's where I'm at, and I hope that gave people time
to think. But as I said, I support this comp
plan as is, as amended, and I also consider other amendments.
Just because other people amend it certain ways doesn't mean that I won't be for
it after those amendments.
Well, then try this one.
You're ready then?
Yes.
I filibustered enough for you, Mayor?
Good.
I really did try. I have some
confusion about what you said, but I followed most of it, I
believe. Okay, never mind. Can I just ask you, Councilor
Pride,
toward the end, it sounded like you were saying
that
you're concerned that... We are basically talking about
upzoning.
No.
What is that?
To make land more valuable because of what it can be
used for.
So I don't-
Well, the old plan does that,
and what we're saying is now we're actually restricting it from being
residential unless they jump through a bunch of hoops.
But where in the old plan did it zone it residential?
It said that the staff should work with them to develop whatever they want.
We should put the land to the most valuable use possible, basically.
We'll have to agree to dance on
this pin top.
It wasn't specific, but it does not restrict it at all.
It says staff should work with-
All right. Well, I see your hand, Councilor Russ.
I was going to offer the motion, but would you like to speak?
Well, I'd just like to point, the land right now, the comprehensive
plan, the 2012 comprehensive plan specifically says mixed use,
and the existing zoning is 86 feet
So, the proposed plan is a significant down
zone
Yes, in the height things, absolutely. Yeah. Yes.
But it never said residential, and now it will.
So anyway, unless-
But only if they meet the-
No, sorry.
It doesn't say residential, per se.
No, it doesn't.
All right. I will just-
No, it doesn't. It makes two years of difference
... offer this.
Right.
It does.
I move to amend the shipyard district language,
the land use language, to add the following, "Residential and
lodging uses within the shipyard district shall not be permitted
unless petroleum storage and transfer operations have been
permanently discontinued."
Do we have a second?
Could you repeat that?
Hold it. Residential and lodging uses within the shipyard district shall
not be permitted
unless petroleum storage and transfer operations have been
permanently discontinued.
That kind of precludes 21, which you said
was the best place for a park along the Fore River.
Thank you-
Excludes, not precludes
... Councilor Coleman, but I think what I need is a second-
No... or no second.
So, so far I don't see a second,
and you're not seconding it either. All right.
So that motion doesn't even become a motion.
Let's try another one, if you would just hear me on this one.
This is with the Section 5C13 language,
and it is not highly specific, but what I
would add to the language is,
"The city shall incorporate air dispersion and
human exposure modeling using best available science
and data reflective of full
permitted or licensed operational capacity
to inform land use decisions, public health assessments, and
future policy development in areas
proximate to petroleum storage and transfer facilities."
I think you're going to have to read that again.
It's not asking for a specific one.
Yeah.
It is suggesting that
as we...
Well, first of all, I don't see a second, so I don't think it's-
Oh, I might. I just need-
You might
... to hear it again.
All right. So we've put in there some
language that says some health
standards must be met. My concern
has always been that
health standards can kind of change depending on what state
you're standing in, depending on what administration you might
have at the state or federal level, depending on whether your lawyer is
better than the other person's lawyer.
So,
with the modeling idea, I think it takes a lot of the data,
and like the weather is forecasted, it
forecasts where
the emissions are going. And I did hear earlier
in this discussion, I'm losing track of who said it, but it
might have even been a staff member. I don't know. No, maybe it was you.
It was Scott. Scott. You talked about
knowing more about dispersion and where it's ending up,
and that's what modeling would help us do. Yes.
I just needed you to reread the language.
Oh, you didn't need a speech?
No.
God darn it. Well, then you came to the wrong person.
"The city shall incorporate air dispersion and human
exposure modeling using best available science and
data reflective of full permitted or
licensed operational capacity to inform land use
decisions, public health assessments, and future policy development
in areas proximate to petroleum storage and transfer
facilities."
Where would that be?
It would be with 5C13.
It doesn't take anything away, it asks us to
incorporate the use of modeling.
Mr. City Manager, on that statement that she
just made,
isn't that similar along the lines of what's been
going on
to work on for the last year and a half?
It was recommended by the CAC.
Separate from the burst emissions
work, and maybe is what you're referencing, that's something that the city is
working with the tank companies and DEP to get
something stood up. It's already underway. This would be different, though.
This would specifically call for the HEM modeling, HEM4 model,
to be
what the city uses to make determinations and also
some other things. So it would-
So this would be a city responsibility, not a business responsibility.
It would depend on how you'd want to frame it, right?
Either the city would have to pay for the cost of the modeling, or somehow the
developer would have to,
as part of the submission, include that modeling.
And excuse me, but isn't that not so unusual to ask the
developer to pay for some kind of testing?
So interesting.
But-
Can you speak into the microphone? I can't hear you.
Oh, sorry.
Thank you.
What Scott just... I was just commenting that I don't think
it's highly unusual to ask the potential
developer to pay for that sort of thing, or maybe it's a 50/50.
I also would mention that I believe this is in line with recommendations
that came from the CAC report.
Excuse me. Was there a second?
I will second that.
She's trying to... Thank you for the second. Woo.
My victory of the evening.
All right. So more discussion and questions. Yes, Councilor West.
Because several of the
people raised issues about modeling, I discussed it with
sources that I have that are knowledgeable
and-The feedback that I
will comply, I will not support this because there are different
ways of modeling, and they're continually evolving, and I
don't think that the city has the expertise to dictate it, and
I just don't think it belongs in a comprehensive plan.
Carter Scott has her hand raised.
Yes, I have a question for the councilor, or maybe it's even a
rebuttal, but let's have Carter speak.
Thank you. I just wanted to comment again that I think the level of
specificity...
Oops, sorry.
I think the level of specificity here with the comprehensive
plan is just too much and instead
of setting a policy goal as 5.C.13
does and sort of enables us to continue to work on this, and maybe we
set a policy or have a workshop and
continue to promote the HEM 4
model. If that model is different in five
years, do we then have to change the comprehensive plan?
So I think
we have a strong policy statement here that we want to move in
this direction. I think we have a council that is in favor
of working towards air quality that supports a healthy
residency. I don't think there's any argument there.
I think when you start to get into that level of specificity, you get into all
the questions about who pays for it, when is it done, how is it
supported? Does the city do it? Does the city work with the
state regulators to do it? I really appreciate it, and I think I would
support us moving forward with the HEM 4 model in some way.
I'd like to learn more about that, but I just don't know that this is the
right venue to set that level of specificity and bind the
council for the next 15 years on a certain path.
So, thank you.
Thank you. And also, I'm trying to be a fair facilitator, but also
make my case. So,
one,
I didn't say HEM 4. I said, "Shall incorporate air
dispersion and human exposure modeling." So it's not that
specific. It's a call for modeling is something to
use when we're trying to make these determinations about potential
health hazards and where the emissions are
going, et cetera. So I'm just wanting to be clear, I
didn't specify in that way. And then
the other question that I would have to the councilors who say, "Well, that doesn't
belong there," is how is saying we should do modeling
different than saying we should do other health
standards? I'm actually asking that question.
Councilor Pride.
I think in a lot of ways, that language was added
as a way of giving something to those folks who were coming to those
meetings and complaining about or I shouldn't say complaining, but making their
opinion known about housing and whatnot in
the comprehensive plan.
I was one of those.
I understand that. And I think it was a way...
Because I don't think this is normal.
And we heard Councilor Scott say she would eliminate the language that's
overly specific in this because she doesn't think it belongs in a comprehensive
plan. And I don't know if I completely agree with that.
I think that there's an extent to which this is a
little more specific than I've seen comprehensive plans, and we can ask Milan
if he thinks this is more specific than a lot of comprehensive plans.
But I don't think there's anything wrong with going a
certain length. I think this just remains vague enough, and the
more we add, the more specific it gets.
But because this was done by the committee, and it's being brought to us
after the committee took in testimony and made changes.
Because I remember the language we heard the last time we spoke about this.
I think there was a CALPUA 27 the last time we heard about the
comp plan when we had that check-in,
and now there isn't anymore. And that happened through deliberations of the
committee and hearing public comment.
And so I'm more okay with that than I am with just us tinkering
with it to add more specificity. On the other hand, I agree with Councilor
Scott again, that if you were to bring forward a workshop, I would may be
the first person to throw up a second to add that to our code of
ordinances.
Yes. An environmental health workshop is something I've had in my head for a little
while. All right. I think we better vote on this motion.
All in favor of the motion-
It's a roll call.
Oh, it's a roll call. Thank you.
You're very welcome.
What-
Repeat the motion
It was the motion, basically the motion to add
modeling as one of the requirements.
It's the city shall incorporate air dispersion and human
exposure modeling using best available science and data
reflective of full permitted or licensed operational capacity,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Do you remember that?
Yes.
Thank you.
All right. Can we have a roll call vote?
Councilor Matthews?
No.
Councilor West?
Councilor Pride?
No.
Councilor Scott?
Councilor Walker?
Yes.
Councilor Coleman?
And Mayor Tipton.
Yes.
All right. The motion does not pass.
That is a four to three vote.
All right. So where are we at now? We are asking if there are
any other changes that are being proposed
to the plan
that we have heard aboutAny other
motions?
Yes, Milan has his hand up. He's motioning.
Well, I'm just ready if you want to take up Councilor Walker's proposed edits to
the timeline.
Okay, thank you.
What page is that?
I think we're ready.
There are a few. I'll read them out.
Yes. Let's hear what you've come up with. Thank you so much, Milan.
So I was able to confirm these are PDF export
issues. We had them in earlier versions, but anyway, they're brought
back here
for you all. So it begins on page
25 with policy 3A.20.
That should be a short-term policy.
The next one is policies 5A.3,
5A.4, and 5A.5,
and those are, in order, ongoing, ongoing, and
medium-term.
The next correction is in 6D.5,
6D.6, 6D.7,
and in order, those would be ongoing, medium, and ongoing.
And that's all.
Okay.
Finals.
Our guest lawyer friend, what are we calling this?
I
would say,
Milan, is it accurate to say this is
how the comprehensive plan should have been presented
this evening?
It's a little bit interesting because theoretically, there could
be some
missed opportunity to comment on those changes if they were
misrepresented
initially. But,
I'm not sure how a sort of minor
element of a proposal would normally be handled in that sort of
situation.
City staff-
But because the council is already considering
sort of discrete amendments, I think it might be appropriate
if the council's in agreement for a council member to make a motion
to amend
the comprehensive plan as actually presented to
incorporate those changes.
I would like to do so.
I'll second that.
Thank you. Just what he said.
Okay. Anything to say?
Who seconded? I'm sorry, I missed it. Milan se-- Excuse me, Misha.
One of those M people.
Councilor Pride. Yeah.
Councilor Pride, thank you.
All right. So anybody else have anything to say about
this?
And that is just to agree to the...
What should've been presented in the first place.
Okay.
Roll call vote. And I think just to clarify on these motions
to amend
in relation to Councilor West's first motion as
well, my understanding is the council has
voted to amend the comprehensive plan, not to adopt
as amended.
So these are preliminary amendments that will take-
So it's-
... as together if all the amendments pass.
But it's not adopting the compre-
Correct... it's only-
Yeah.
Thank you.
Right now.
Yeah. Right.
Okay.
I think we-
Should we get a motion on the floor?
... still are needing a-
I'll do the roll call to accept that.
Yes.
Correct.
Exactly.
When we get back to it.
All right.
Councilor Scott?
Oop. Can't hear. Volume.
Try again.
Lou Scott, go ahead.
Yes, and thank you.
Okay. Councilor Walker?
Yes.
Councilor Coleman?
Councilor Pride?
Yes.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Yes, ma'am.
And Mayor Tipton.
Yes.
Thank you very much.
Okay, any other adjustments, I'll
call them?
Amendments, adjustments.
All right.
I thought we were going to... It's
like one, two, three, four.
And so we're still doing-
Yes
... adopting clear revisions on number two?
Yes.
Okay.
Yes. I think that is well put.
All right. I think then that-
Councilor Scott
... Councilor Scott.
Scott's hand is up.
I have a question.
Yes, Councilor Scott?
Unless other people have further commentary, I would
move to adopt the amended
comprehensive plan as has been amended.
I think we sort of have that motion already.
We had that motion at the beginning.
It was seconded, then we've done all our amendments, and I think now we're
heading to the end.
Okay. Thank you. That's fine.
Thank you very much.
And
that's what I was asking because I have been getting,
and we had 21 speakers tonight,
but there's a very large population that
really is very upset that
Palupa 27 wasn't given a
real...
Because that satisfied.
Mm-hmm.
Would we, if we adopt that, still enable
the Save Our Shipyard people to be working because they are
actually working on
how to purchase a-The shipyard district.
Mm-hmm.
And they are making some real strides in
doing that. Their expectation isn't that the
city pays for the whole thing. This is what I'm hearing from
them. And
because it's the people's plan,
they would like to see this land preserved and also
used for marine purposes, which CaLUPA
27 did.
Are you making a motion to consider that?
Yes.
All right. Well, then that clarifies things.
Which is option number three, which is to
continue for substantial amendments, because I believe
that revisiting CaLUPA 27 would
be that.
Madam Mayor.
I think what we have right now, hang on for one second, is
adopt with revisions, has been
motioned and seconded. Then we did some
revisions, so hold that thought-
Okay
... for one second. Milan?
I just want to be clear. The presenters that you heard, or speakers that you
heard come up speak to CaLUPA 27, referenced the staff proposed
CaLUPA 27. But you also had in circulation before the
meeting, another CaLUPA 27 that was
community-generated, that has not been vetted and not been reviewed
by the CPC. It's a very interesting read.
I think it's developed and it's good, but
I know there are specific things that I would
recommend against including, and even to keep the substantive
message the same, just the way it's expressed has some problems.
So
for the council's benefit and mine, I'd really want to know which
CaLUPA 27 we're talking about. The months ago presented
staff proposal,
or the community-recommended proposal that-
I believe this is the community-generated.
That's for sure.
And they,
because-
Excuse me for just one second. Because
what you could do right now is come up with some kind of a motion,
and you are absolutely welcome to do that.
If there's any kind of motion to be considered that would
amend the plan, because would be a
revision to the plan, because right now,
adopt with revisions has been motioned.
So if there is something that you want to add as an
amendment to the idea of adopting with revisions,
and it would be a revision-
Yeah
... that's what we can do now. But we can't do anything other than that.
Okay, because that's why I was asking before, because
I understand that this would have to go back to the
comprehensive plan to review the
community plan
as, as you said, because they wanted to be
able to actually continue. They've made quite
a bit of strides-
Well, yes
... in even towards purchasing that property.
Can I ask a clarification question to Milan?
Yeah.
So should we adopt this with revisions tonight?
That doesn't prevent us from changing things should they make good progress with
the package, correct?
As far as zoning and stuff on there, and lifting some of the
barriers that would prevent people from...
Obviously,
we can't control what the package want to do with their
property right now. These guys are making good
talks, good conversation and everything, and I get that.
One of my biggest fear, I haven't talked much tonight at all, but I'm just going to
say this.
I'm glad to hear your voice.
One of my biggest fears is this, is it's taken three and a half years.
They've done a great job. They've put their hearts and soul into it.
Mm-hmm.
50% of those emails that we got supported
development.
50% didn't want development. A lot more of the people who
don't want development showed up tonight. I get that.
But
this isn't going to be perfect, people, because none of one of you guys are
perfect. I'm not perfect, and we're not going to make perfect decisions.
Okay? But my biggest fear is this. The last time we met
on this was last June, almost a year ago, correct?
We have three council seats up in November, and if we continue to kick this
down the road, there could be three new councilors that could change the entire
course of this comprehensive plan.
So really,
let's just
buck down here and make some decisions.
I hear what you're saying, but I also have been hearing from
a lot of people, and this is an opportunity
to preserve our waterfront and also create a
monument.
Can I just make a suggestion?
Yeah.
Yes, please.
Well, if you feel strongly about it, Councilor Coleman, you can vote against this
motion. And if it fails, then you can make your own motion to send it back to
the committee.
Okay.
Yes. Or she could make a motion now because-
If she had specific language, but I haven't heard the specific language yet.
I
don't think we have, I should say.
I expect that it's going to fail-
Because we have a second, but we have to continue voting
... from just the comments here.
Final vote on the main motion.
But I am representing a really large-
Keep trying
... group of people.
All right.
Can I speak?
Yes, please, Councilor Whelan.
Can we table the motion that Counselor West made
and allow Counselor Coleman to bring her motion forward?
Because then we have an answer.
I think we all feel like we have an answer, but we could answer
that and then move forward.
If Councilor-
Hold on
... Coleman's motion is to
revise something, she can make it now and we can-
It's not a revision
... do that. But if her motion is to say-
Ah
... we actually want to do continue and amend-
Yeah
... we're not going to move to that until
we finish with-
Oh, my God
... whether we're voting for the motion already on the table.
I understand.
Okay.
I remove my suggestion.
Everybody get that? There's going to be a test.
All right.
I don't want to close down the idea that you're making a motion,
Councillor Coleman, but I can't really think of what it
should be.
It's the option three.
In that case then, if I may, Mayor.
Please.
In that case, I would
echo that the right course would be for
the counselor to vote how she wishes and then make a new
motion to send it back to the committee
if that motion fails. If the motion to adopt as
amended discreetly fails, then a new motion
could arise.
I get that.
Okay, so to be blunt, we're about to vote on the
motion that's on the table.
Yes.
You don't know how that motion will go. I don't either.
I have some ideas of how it will go. But we can't have
you motion to-
Yes, I know
... continue and amend until we have that vote.
That's why I was asking before because...
Okay. All right.
I motion.
All right. Thank you. I think we are clear, and unless
anyone has further comments, I think we're at the time where we're
voting, and we need to do a roll call vote.
Councillor Matthews?
Yes.
Councillor West?
Councillor Pride?
Yes.
Councillor Scott?
Councillor Walker?
Yes.
Councillor Coleman?
No.
Mayor Tipton?
That fails.
Passes.
No.
Okay, so the motion has passed, the motion
to adopt with revisions. We made the
revisions,
and that is where we are.
And I should say that with more surety, but it's
been a night. So that is where we are
now.
And is there
anything else before we would end this part of the
meeting?
All right. Yes, Milan?
Just again, for wrapping it up, our next step would be to
package it up with the amendments and send it off to the state for
certification. We'd report that out to you at a future council meeting report out.
Yes, Councillor Pride, do you want to say something?
I would like to make a motion that we postpone the remainder of the
agenda, and I'd move to adjourn.
How much more did we have left?
It's after 11:00.
It's after 11:00, so-
Just accepting donations, though.
11:35.
Aren't we just accepting donations?
I can go on the next agenda.
All right. Well, if somebody is supporting Councillor
Pride's motion?
I will.
Yes.
Yep.
Seconded?
Yes.
All right. Do we need an actual roll call vote for that?
I think we do, unless, Councillor Pride, you wanted to make
comments.
Roll call vote. Councillor Matthews?
Yes.
Councillor West?
Councillor Pride?
Yes.
Councillor Scott?
Councillor Walker?
Yes.
Councillor Coleman?
Mayor Tipton?
Yes. Thank you.
Thank you, everyone. We will
go onward together in South Portland, the city that we
love.
If I start S and G, then it's just going to be dangerous because we don't know what
we'll get.
No, but I just didn't think so, but it's after 11:00.
Well, the rule-
Yeah, the rule is supposed to-
After 11:00, yeah
... we were supposed to have a motion.
We went the backwards way.
Right. We were supposed to.
But I wasn't going to bring it up.
My watch is, my watch-